But then I haven't got
everybody on, have I?
Sorry?
Haven't got everybody on to do the-
Yeah, we need
to
We're just waiting for the live stream.
You're a long way away.
I know.
Hello. Hello.
So, just before we start, one of the reasons for that was we thought that other
room, last time there were people standing, and we thought of this as a bigger
room. But it just means that we're sort of here
to here.
But we do have members coming online as well, so yeah. Great.
Right. So, just before we start, I'm just seeking leave.
We've got a couple of people from committee members.
We've got a couple of people who have asked to take photos, and I'm
seeking leave from the committee.
There's one member of the public and one member from Tim's office.
Are people okay with that?
Good? Yep. That's fine. Thank you. Okay, welcome.
Welcome to our hearing here with Fire and Emergency this
afternoon. We are starting, and welcome, Ravin.
It's your first time in front of our committee, and I'm sorry to hear that your
plane got canceled, but it's lovely that we've got the technology for you to come
in online.
Thank you very-
So,
we've got five minutes to start with you, and then we'll open up with
all of your opening remarks, and then we'll open from there,
according to the structured agenda for questions.
So, I'll hand to whoever is going to start with the opening
remarks.
I will start, Madam Chair. Thank you.
And I do apologize. This is indeed my first
appearance and,
I very much would have preferred to be there in person.
But
Fire and Emergency welcomes the opportunity to continue assisting in this
inquiry.
In the room with yourselves
is the Chief Executive and National Commander, Kerry Gregory;
Deputy Chief Executive, Megan Stifler; and Chief
Financial Officer, Darryl Purdy.
At the previous appearance, Fire and Emergency described the
challenge of managing a large, specialized, and
nationally dispersed fleet,
including continuing pressure around the Type 3 and
aerial appliances.
Today, I want to acknowledge those challenges, set out what has
changed, and what remains to be done.
When I first looked at this issue, I thought, "This must be simple.
We're just buying a truck. How hard can it be?" But a fire
appliance is not simply a truck. It is a bespoke,
complex machine operating in difficult environment.
It is clear Fire and Emergency's fleet experience has been affected
by procurement and contract management challenges,
supplier performance, and COVID disruptions.
Those factors have a very long tail, and that long tail
is the reason why we are here. The Type 3 decisions were made in
good faith when Fire and Emergency needed to renew an aging
fleet and get appliances on the road.
But the two-stage chassis and body build
approach has not delivered the timeliness, the
reliability, or clarity of accountability that
was intended.
Would we approach these parts of that program
differently now? Definitely.
But we must pick the resultant issues up, address them,
learn from them, and make the best decisions from here.
In my short time as Chair, three weeks, I have raised
these matters with the chief executive and have been briefed on the
reviews and changes that have already been made.
Our focus will be on stronger contract management,
clearer escalation of risks,
better fault information reporting, disciplined
acceptance processes, and greater board visibility
of major programs.
For future complex appliance, Fire and Emergency should,
where practicable, favor more integrated or
turnkey procurement models
with clearer accountability for the complete appliance.
That does not mean removing operational input.
Firefighters' expertise remain essential in defining requirements,
testing suitability, training crews, and confirming
readiness.
It means applying that input at the right stages with clear
decision rights.
I do not want to suggest that all the problems have been solved, because they
have not.
The legacy tail will continue, and further issues may emerge.
Indeed, we have paused the rollout of the Type 3s following
discovery of a filter issue in operational testing,
which the supplier is now working through.
Like I said, it's not just buying a new truck.
The board's responsibility is to ensure the organization responds quickly,
applies lessons across the fleet, and provides the oversight
required for the aerial program and future procurement.
There is also wider funding challenges.
Fire and Emergency responds to a broader range of emergencies these days,
while maintaining a specialized heavy fleet.
The minister has
commissioned a review
of the funding mechanism. We will provide evidence about the
investment challenge, recognizing that the options available
involve difficult choices. Madam Chair, my
approach today is straightforward.
We will not minimize the experience of firefighters or communities.
We will acknowledge the concerns,
be factual about how we arrived here, and be clear about
what has changed and what remains to be done.
Our focus is stronger procurement,
better information, clearer accountability, and sustained
governance oversight.
I am reassured that overall, Fire and Emergency
continues to respond effectively to emergency events.
I want to close by thanking the thousands of career and volunteer firefighters
who work together to keep our communities safe,
and the people across Fire and Emergency who support them.
Thank you, and we look forward to assisting the committee.
Thank you. Thank you very much, Ravin.
And we also would've loved to have seen you in person, but
next time.
And you might notice that we've got some members as well
online, for similar reasons as well.
So there's a few of us here and then some online.
So I'm just going to say to members online that can you please,
if you've got a question, can you please put your virtual hand up and I will be
watching that as well. But we're going to start with
the first part of the structured agenda, which is the current and future
strategy and capital planning. And I think, Tim, you have the first-
Thanks
... question.
Thanks, Madam Chair.
Thank you, Ravin, thanks defense staff who are attending here.
I'll just start.
Fundamental question, is fleet a strategic priority for
FENZ?
Yes.
Why is it not listed in the national strategy as a
strategic priority?
If you look at the national strategy, it talks to building stronger business
foundations. Fleet is part of those stronger business foundations that we're
building for the organization.
Right. So
as I try to unpick this and understand it, there's a few documents that sort of
cover fleet. There's the
asset management plan.
Mm-hmm.
And then there's a fleet strategy,
and then there's the future operating capability.
So
correct me if I've got this wrong, the fleet strategy
is yet to come out. That will go to the, is it next year we're expecting that
to go to the board for approval?
Correct. The fleet strategy, itself hasn't been developed yet.
And the reason for that is that it's been important for the organization to
get a good picture of our assets through the asset management plan.
So over the last few years we've been developing the asset management
plans, one of those being the fleet asset management plan.
And that gives a really defined 10-year journey of
how we reduce the age of the fleet to within
90% of it within the target age of that.
So I guess the approach up to this point has been very
much a
like for like replacement
of our assets. But certainly as we move forward,
those three things you mentioned, the asset management plans, the future
operating capability, and the fleet strategy itself will form
the grouping of documents that will help guide us as an
organization around the strategy of how we ensure
that
we're developing the right long-term strategy.
So I understand what you're saying.
Is it the right way around, though?
If your future operating capability
is designed to consider more broadly the service requirements and
what it is that it looks like in the future-
Mm-hmm
... surely you would start from that, then you would build out what your fleet
strategy is to enable that, and then you could come up with the asset management
plan because the asset management plan, as you say, is like for like.
Mm-hmm.
But without those sort of defined and agreed levels of service, we're
talking about assets with a 20-year,
20 to 25 lifespan that take a long time to
introduce.
Mm-hmm.
Don't we need to start by looking at 2040, 2050 and starting from
that rather than an asset management plan that is built on like for like when we
know that like for like probably isn't the answer?
So I think in the initial stages of the organization coming together
in 2017 and the
legacy of fleet assets that we inherited through there,
stabilizing the fleet
needs to be the initial focus of that.
So you're right in an ideal world, that looking out
seems the logical thing to do, but making sure that we can stabilize the
fleet first so that we actually can
build the rest of the information that needs to build that fleet strategy.
And that's around what's the
long-term context and how that's changing, and we've seen lots of changes
in the way that we're being asked to deploy into communities.
That's looking at a risk-based profile rather
than just a like for like across the longer term.
And it also looking at things like affordability,
and the longer term maintenance costs of all of that asset base.
So it's affordability lens put across that as well.
So
the fleet, you've described the fleet asset
management plan as a deliberate forward-looking roadmap for managing fleet over the
next decade.
Yep.
And it clearly distinguishes between what is required and what can be delivered.
Mm-hmm.
But, and we'll get into type specific stuff further on, but
do we actually know,
until we define what those sort of service delivery
levels are, until we know what the appliances
actually need-
Mm-hmm
...
we're not forward looking and we're not distinguishing between what is
required and what can be delivered because if you look at the aerial fleet,
the
asset specifications were not static inputs.
In other words, what we were looking for changed as the project went on.
So surely we have to start with that capability definition, don't we?
Mm-hmm. But I think it's
hard in any organization to forecast what the end result's going to be,
and it will be an evolving thing as we move forward.
But getting the asset management plans in place and having an
understanding around
what's the long-term plan to reduce that age of a fleet
has been really important to ensure that we're focused in the right places while we
build the next book. So there's been a lot of
pieces of intelligence or information missing from the organization
that's allowed us to bring all that together to actually form a robust
strategy. And that is where the future operation capability,
the asset plans, now we have a really good picture of that,
come together, which will help us develop,
not a
simple strategy, but a more mature strategy that sets us up for the future and
allows us to look at what are the changing context and how
do we make those critical investment decisions and trade-offs
as we move to a different way of operating as the context changes around
us as an organization.
I guess my fundamental concern is that we sort of have a culture, and it's not
just within FENZ and FENZ-
Mm
... of providing administrative solutions to mechanical problems.
Mm.
We add more layers of paper and things that achieve compliance, and yet we've
got an asset management plan, but has it helped?
I don't know. I'd argue maybe it hasn't.
We have all these sort of layers and then think,
all these bits of paper, are they actually making it
any better when you go to the local fire station? And...
Well, personally, I think the asset management plans have helped in that
there's a real detailed plan around how we bring that age profile of the
fleet over the next 10 years. We didn't have that prior to the asset management
plans.
So, that gives a really good picture that sits in there.
If we look at the
development of the FOC work, that's another big piece of work
that'll actually look at not just a
one-size-fits-all, but
looking at what the risk is and how we apply different capabilities to
different risk. So, that will inform the asset management plans around the
decisions that could be made in there.
So,
if you haven't got that work, you need to develop it to make a difference.
The difference that people will see on the ground floor, that firefighters will
see, and I certainly acknowledge the frustration that our
firefighters have. When we've got an aging fleet and they're breaking down at
times, that's so frustrating. I've been in the situation myself, so
I, in no way,
disregard the frustration that our firefighters feel when they have
appliances break down. And that's why there's needed to be a focus on how do we
stabilize that first? How do we actually focus on ensuring
that the appliances that we're rolling out the door
aren't breaking down, we're bringing them with an age profile.
And that's not a short-term fix. Like I say, we've got a 10-year plan that's really
definitive about that.
And just final one if I can, and then so how would,
given these things you say they are actually adding value-
Mm
... how would you assess FENZ is going against your asset management goals?
Say that question again, sorry.
How would you assess FENZ is doing against your asset
management goals?
Oh, against the asset management goals.
Well, I think,
what we're doing is we're building the foundations to make us successful in the
space. If I look at some of the procurements that we've had
over the past years, the things like the Type 1s, the Type 2s, they've
been really good procurement
end-to-end processes. Our Type 3s has just been
frustrating for everybody, and taken far longer than anyone would've
anticipated that to have take or that's acceptable for that to take.
But it's learning from the different processes and putting those in place so that
we are applying what's working well and
improving as we move forward. The asset management plans, that's going to
stand us in really good stead to actually have confidence that
over a 10-year plan, we're going to bring the assets age to that, but we can't do
it overnight, and that's the frustration.
Sorry, I meant the specific five asset management goals that you have.
How we're going against them?
Yes.
I'd have to come back to you with the
response on that. I don't want to mislead the committee and-
No, that's fine. Are you aware of the five asset management goals?
Mm-hmm.
Can you just give us an example of one of those goals and then how
you would assess how you're going?
I can't give them verbatim, but, Daryl, have you got those there?
It's in the asset management plan.
No. You've got five asset management goals that are listed in your
10-year plan, 2020 to 2030.
In the 10-year plan. So in our asset management fleet plan, you're talking about?
No, in the
FENZ...
Yeah, it'll be up there.
I'm not sure which document you're referring to.
In your 10-year plan, 2020 to 2030,
page 38 will have your asset management goals.
Oh, the 10-year plan has been superseded by the
strategy.
So that's the national strategy, but that's 2019 to 2045.
That starts a year earlier.
It's been superseded by the current strategy that
takes us through to 2030, so from '25 to 2030.
So that was a
preexisting document.
Right. So does the 2019 to 2045 strategy still,
is that still a thing?
We only have one organizational strategy, which is the current strategy.
Which is the '25 to '30?
Yes.
So the one that went out to 2045 is gone?
So the current strategy is
only a five-year plan?
Yes.
And that recognizes the fact that in a five-year continuum,
things change. Things are changing really fast and that thing.
So having a strategy that goes out to 2045, I
would say that no one could predict what 2045 would look like for us as an
organization.
But isn't that the point of future operating capability, is to look out to say,
because the assets that you buy are going to be operating in 2050
2050 plus.
So future operating capability is different from our current
strategy, which takes us through to 2030.
What we're doing as an organization is, the organization has tried to
do too much and hasn't been focused.
So having a clear focus through our strategy for the next five years, or the
five years of the time of the strategy, to actually ensure that the
organization's focusing on the right things to take
us forward. And that is looking at our safe, resilient, effective services
that we have. Looking at our role as a regulator and in prevention.
Looking at
stronger relationships and working with other agencies and
communities. It is about
making sure that we've got stronger business foundations,
and it's about supporting our people to be effective
through our business.
Okay.
So I've got a follow-up here.
Yeah.
Mike Davidson.
But to that, the fleet strategy, when was the
decision to actually do a fleet strategy made?
Well, there's been lots of discussion around a fleet strategy.
And it goes right back even to the
International Convention Center fire, where through there, there was a
recommendation that we needed to have a fleet strategy in place.
The realization of
actually developing a fleet strategy showed that we first needed to
have things like the asset management plans,
and we needed to have the future operating capability work that informs
those to actually bring it all together.
Otherwise, we're putting together a fleet strategy
that won't effectively... It'll sit in a drawer and it won't be effective because
it's not having the right
injects in it to actually inform it to allow us to be successful in that.
Okay.
We're going to Lamona on screen.
Thanks, Madam Chair. Hopefully you can hear me.
Yes, very good.
And hopefully I'll continue to follow on.
I would like to know from the explanation this
morning and from the new board chair's opening words in terms
of the strategy that is supposedly, and hopefully I've heard it properly,
fit for purpose, because lots of the feedback
that I've had as a member of parliament, but also from the community, is in
terms of what is relevant and what is out of date.
And
all of us around the select committee have had a number of concerns raised by many
different various firefighters. We've visited fire stations.
How relevant, in terms of the five-year strategy, will that be
in terms of moving forward? So, appreciate your explanation to the
CEO. However, at this time,
since the inquiry or before it began, it is really
important that you've got a theoretical
base or moving forward in terms of the strategy and fleet management, et cetera,
reading all the documents in. So I'd like to hear from CEO, please.
Yeah, thank you. Appreciate the question.
If I'm interpreting the question right, I think if you're looking
at real material gains, the asset management
plans give a really good
plan around how over the next 10 years we're actually going to bring
the asset age
up. Of course, 90% of our appliances into the
determined asset age. So I think that gives a really good
way in which we're going to move the fleet forward.
Having that information and having that plan allows us to actually
give effect to it now over the next few years.
Supplementary, Madam Chair?
Yes.
Thank you for the replies. In terms of the workforce, I might
be asking out of turn, Madam Chair.
No, just ask it and I'll rule it in or out if I-
Okay. Thank you. So in terms of the workforce, I
want to ask questions around training and planning,
and what is scheduled. We have had answers during
the recent hearings, but I would like to
ask, in terms of will the whole training and
development and workforce, will those sections of your
overall plan, when do they come in?
And how effective are they in terms of rolling out?
So I've heard the questions that you've asked earlier.
You've got a five-year window. How is that built into the current
environment of firefighters
and training and development?
Yeah.
It's on the border of a fleet inquiry.
But if you can bring it, if there's an answer that brings it into scope, or
if you think it's out of scope, if there's anything that brings it in.
Yeah, no, I'm happy to answer the question, and I think it
is relevant as far as when we
bring operational appliances on board,
there's a training component that sits in there as-
Yeah
... ensuring that people understand the new technology and the new components and
that. But if I talk about training itself,
with a workforce of
14,000 people,
and of those 11,800 roughly are
volunteers, it does bring some unique challenges to training,
in the training
system, I guess, that we have as an organization.
So,
you will notice from the literature that one of the areas that we're reinvesting
into, so that we're trying to create some space to reinvest in,
is around training. And we've been doing a lot of good work
around training, and
even speaking with the committee last year when we looked at the
work that we'd done to go back to a
Category IV GTE around the
moderation and assessment work in our training.
Lots of,
I guess- bespoke improvements across training, but not looking at the
training system as a whole. So the training system as a whole
is going to be a multi-year program,
because it's,
I guess in a way similar to fleet, when foreign emergency came
together,
it brought different training environments and approaches from all the
different entities that came in, and foreign emergencies never
really looked at that as the system and saying, "What does our training system need
to look like?" And that's where our investment and time and energy's going in at
the moment, and it's a focus of mine, it's a focus of
the DCE responsible for that, and it's a focus of the board,
which is why it's one of those areas of reinvestment for us as an organization.
Thank you.
Thank you. And next question's from Andy Foster.
Yeah, look, thank you. I'm just looking at,
in terms of you're thinking about strategy, one of the things that you said to us
that you don't know what the future's going to look like, and you then gave us an
answer which talked about business foundations, supporting your people to be
effective, relationships, and all sorts of other things like that.
I didn't hear anything there at all about fleet, although I'm assuming
that supporting our people to be effective, which was the words you used, I think-
Mm
... means you're actually going to have some fire engines that actually work for
people to do their work.
In what
possible scenario is there in future that you are not going to
need the kind of fire engines that you're using at the moment?
You're certainly going to need aerials.
Mm-hmm.
Probably more so than now, because if intensification continues.
You're certainly going to need your Type Threes, but you're going backwards at the
moment. You've been going backwards since FENZ was established.
Thank you, and
if I look at the
essence of your question,
firstly, when I talk about stronger business foundations, that is about our fleet,
and that is about
how we build a fleet that actually supports our
organization, supports our firefighters to do the phenomenal work that they do
across the country every day.
What I would say in there is that,
if you talk about the changing environment,
and yes, I take your point around the current fleet that we have,
is going to be required in the years to come, and that's why we've got a current
focus on stabilizing the fleet that
we've got. Our
asset management plans with the 10-year plan will move the state
of the fleet up. It will make a difference in there, and that's why we've developed
that work.
But some of the things that need to be considered there, and I'll get Megan
to talk about this in a minute, but you look at the role that foreign
emergency plays in weather events at the moment for as an instance.
You spoke about aerial appliances.
What role does drones play in that?
So there's a lot of questions that need to be answered as
technology advances, as things go on, rather than just a status
quo. But do you want to speak, Megan, just a little bit around some of the things
you're seeing and considering as part of what our assets-
Sure
... and portfolio might look like?
Yeah. Thanks, Kerry.
When I first came to foreign emergency, it was
evident that we had to, as Kerry has mentioned, stabilize our
existing fleet because it was beyond the age that where we wanted it.
Part of the work I'm really proud to lead on behalf of operational
response is who do we need to be in the future, and that's what's coming
out of the FOC work.
As firefighters, if we go back 20 years, we would never have thought
our role would’ve been 45% motor
vehicle and medical.
So that shows you how quickly our industry changes.
What the FOC, Future Operating Capability, is wanting to do
is cast out about what could happen in our future, then
bring it back into reasonable time frames.
So, for example,
where will
technology take us as firefighters in 10, 20 years?
Then bring it back into a reasonable five year.
What can we do over the next five years that progresses us
towards that future?
We have technology, we have the built environment, it is
all created at a very fast pace,
and for us to imagine what it's going to look like in
2040,
we'd be aiming for something that mightn't exist.
So I think the five-year frames is reasonable.
It gives us enough time to procure new fleet or equipment, and gives us
enough time to also train our people appropriately for that
capability that we see ahead.
Great.
So look, if I can just follow up with a sup there.
You said 20 years ago that a lot of your, you wouldn't have considered that, what
do you, I think you said 45% of your role medical, motor vehicle, et cetera?
Yes.
But that doesn't mean that your firefighting role has
diminished, that just means something else has been added on top of it.
Which does go to the issue, which is not part of this inquiry, but does go to the
issue of how FENZ is funded, which I'm very grateful the minister has
actually taken that up. But the incidence of fire
hasn't gone away, and I don't think you would be telling me it's
diminished either.
No.
You've still got to have vehicles that are fit for purpose to do that core
part of your job.
Yes. Thank you. And, I agree with you, and that is why
our focus has been on stabilizing our core fleet.
There will be potentially other demands on what are the
capabilities that we need through that, but at the end of the day,
our primary responsibility under the legislation
sits in there around fire, and that will always be at the core of what we
do. The size of the network and how that network
distribution looks-
is something that needs to be considered as far as what's the risk
profile of the different areas. There's a big difference between
the
risk profile in a really isolated rural
community to that in the heart of a major city.
So the type of appliances, the type of equipment isn't just a
one-size-fits-all.
I get that.
Yeah.
I get that. But at the moment, when you talk about stabilizing your fleet, you are
still going backwards because the rate at which you should be replacing the fleet
to keep you under
your age cap, you should be progressing forwards, but you've been going backwards
essentially since FENZ started, certainly with the Type Threes and with the
aerials.
You're correct with Type Threes, certainly.
If you look at the graphs that we've provided in there across the Type
Ones and Twos in the rural fleet, we've been holding the line in there.
That's why I didn't include them.
Yep. But with the Type Threes, like I said before,
it has been very frustrating and
the time that it's taken because of a number of reasons to
actually get those Type Threes on the run,
and procured and into New Zealand, has been a
challenge for us as an organization.
Okay, thank you.
I'll come back on those things later on.
Okay, thanks, Andy. And I've got two more primaries in this
section, the first being from Tim.
Thank you. Just for the board chair,
one of your goals you said at the start was about having greater board visibility.
So in the
initial hearing to this inquiry, I asked the then board chair
if she and if the board had been asking questions about the
Type Three man trucks,
the same questions that we had been asking the last couple of years, and she
emphatically told me yes, and that she was just as concerned as we were.
In the response to question 40 that I submitted after that
hearing, where I asked for the reference from those board
meetings, there are none after December 2023.
So
how do you explain that?
Thank you for the question.
As you would appreciate, it is very difficult for me
to explain
what happened previously. Firstly, because I haven't put
my mind to it, and secondly, I wasn't there.
But I think the intention of your question,
I can address that. It is my expectation
that the organization, when we appear before Parliament, we
provide information that is accurate,
complete, and readily understandable.
And if there's uncertainty, we will say so.
If the numbers change, we will explain why,
and if we discover an error, we will correct it
promptly. So I cannot speak for the
past, but I want to give you assurance
that the organization that I am chair of, my expectations
will be very clear that when we tell this
committee or anyone in Parliament that we have
had a certain degree of oversight, we should be able to provide the
evidence to prove that.
Yeah, but my fundamental question is, has the board
had, the board that you now lead, I appreciate it wasn't you at the time, but have
they had the appropriate level of oversight?
Because we have not been given any evidence that suggests that for all of
2024 and all of 2025, this topic was even raised once.
Yeah.
Thank you. What I'm saying is, I do not have an answer to that
here now, but either the chief executive of the offices
may have that, but we can always bring the information to you.
Sure.
And Kerry has his hand up, so I'm going to hand to him.
Thank you, Chair. And, yeah, I just wanted to
add into that conversation that the board has been holding us to account
through their financial investment and sustainability committee,
so the subcommittee of the board.
And that feeds up through to
the minister's office has been having a
lot of focus on us as an organization and what we're doing in fleet and the
interest as part of those discussions that we have with her on a regular
basis.
But the main
focus for the board has been through their FISC committee.
I understand that answer.
The issue that we have is that
it's a really clear question that has been submitted in writing.
Can the board please share minutes of meetings where they have asked FENZ staff
about tranche two man Type Three appliances?
And there are quite a few between 2017 and
2023. There's nothing beyond that.
And this is the only tool that the public have for oversight, is the board.
And I think there is a genuine concern out there as to whether or not they've been
doing their function. Does the board have the right people, the right capability,
the right skills and experience to actually fulfill the role that they hold?
What would your view as the chair be?
Well, thank you. As Chair, I would say that I agree that
the board needs to have the appropriate skills
to function and to provide that
rigorous
oversight on assurance, accountability, and execution.
Do you currently have that?
I would not know, and so it would be
improper for me to provide a judgment at this stage.
Thank you.
We've got one more question in this section, and so we're coming
to the end, so I'll hand over to Mike.
Yeah, thank you. And I've just got a couple of little subs to follow on from-
Yeah
... Beth Foster. And I guess it was the comment you made around holding the
line
with your,
I guess the initial nine years around the oil and other appliances
apart from Type 3. Was that a
directive to hold the line over that period of time, or were you actually meant
to improve
the standard of the fleet?
Well, certainly, if you look at the Type 3s, the
intention of the Type 3s was to procure-
Oh, sorry, I'm not talking about the Type 3s.
You were saying the other
appliances, you're holding the line.
Mm-hmm.
You've held the line.
Yeah.
Was that a directive to hold the line and just actually keep it
at the state they were in, or you meant to actually
improve the standard of the fleet?
Well, the aspiration is always to improve it.
But, we are balancing the fleet across all of the asset
classes and the prioritization across those asset classes.
And we've-
I guess I'm wondering, I looked at, and you mentioned in the
submission that you've invested 114 million over the last
nine years.
Mm.
And if you look at your total revenue you've received over that nine years,
it's circa 6.3 billion, so this equates to
1.8%.
Mm.
Do you think that was enough to be going into the fleet during the last nine years?
Especially when you look forward and you're budgeting
356 million over the next 10 years and saying that's
154 million short.
Mm.
Do you think you were budgeting
enough over the last nine years-
Mm
... to actually
move forward in the right direction?
I'll pass to Gerald to
fill in around the
allocation of the different finances in the different areas.
But what I would say is that,
what we've been balancing there is investment in the right parts of the
organization to keep moving it forward.
And, if we'd invested more into the fleet,
the question of that is, where does it fall over somewhere else?
So, in balancing and the fiscal parameters that
we have, making the right decisions, I think the balancing across the
fleet,
has led us to the situation we are. And whether that could've been different-
So do you think the fact we're here today means that it wasn't balanced correctly?
Well, do you want to talk about how we've balanced that, Gerald, across the
different areas?
It's a simple question.
Mm.
How it was balanced in the past to basically put 1.8% of the total
revenue towards fleet, do you think that was the right call in hindsight?
I think that the reason that we are here today is
predominantly because of the challenges that we've had around the Type 3 fleet, and
that doesn't necessarily come into the investment in there.
It comes into some of the challenges and issues we've had being able
to find the right solution and get that put in place.
So yes, I do think that the balance across the asset portfolio has been right.
So you're saying if we didn't have the issues with the Type 3, you wouldn't be
sitting at this end of the table right now?
We'd obviously still be reporting to select committee, but
I don't think we'd be having the same discussions today that we would be having.
Okay. I think I've got it primarily now.
We were hoping that we'd see the national fleet manager today, but our
understanding is he's resigned and left,
which I guess was a bit of a surprise at the time.
Did he give his required contracted notice
period
before he left?
Certainly, the
national manager left and we were
comfortable with the notice that he gave us as an organization.
And there was-
Was it the same as the contracted notice period?
I don't know that information. I'd have to have a look at what his particular
contract was with us in that regard.
Did he receive an exit package that would be greater than just his holiday
pay?
The national manager did a really good job for us as an
organization in actually ensuring that all the
assets, like, it'd been with us well before Foreign
Emergency came into existence. So bringing all those
assets into the organization and making
sure that we had the ability to function.
He gave a lot of service to the organization and,
when he advised that he'd decided to step down of his own accord,
then we were happy to accept that request from
him and-
Who did he report to?
He reported to the deputy chief executive,
of assets.
And during his tenure, did he raise any
concerns with how the fleet was progressing in
terms of obviously the age of it?
There was certainly, we had visibility around the age of the fleet, yes.
So he raised concerns?
He raised the challenge around the aging nature of the fleet and the
ability to deal with that aging profile.
Which, like I said, the asset management plans have been developed to
actually give us a plan around,
and that's been over the last three years they've been developed to actually give
us a plan around how we work ourselves out of that as an
organization.
Yeah.
And that DCE, is she still employed by Fence?
No, the DCE is-
She's also left?
She has also left, yeah.
Did she also receive
remuneration on exit higher than holiday
pay?
I haven't seen that anyone's received a-
We haven't seen that either
... remuneration payment, but-
But you can tell us now that they haven't, if you like. I'll give you the chance.
No, the DCE has not received any extra remuneration.
She's gone on to another role, which is super awesome.
Why did we never see her at this inquiry in any of the previous hearings, given
the focus was fleet?
Well, the last,
select committee that we had, she was on annual leave over that period of time, so
she wasn't available for that. But you have
previously had
One of our fleet specialists in that field, when I didn't
attend the
select committee.
Okay, we're going to move now to the next section, which
is type three appliances, including how chassis were
selected, body build, and allocations to stations.
Was there anything that you wanted to say first in this section?
No, I'm happy to take questions and then-
Okay. Great
Thank you
... a couple more-
Thank you, Tim.
So the committee's agreed, we're going to go through just a bit of a timeline for
the type three. And in the interest of time and the number of questions we might
have, I might just start with tranche two.
So,
as I understand, tranche two began in August
2019 when, is it Penske or Penske? I
apologize, I don't know how to pronounce it.
Effectively rang up and said, "It's now or never if you want some more of the
NA16 cab chassis." Is that
correct?
I understand that there was an opportunity for the organization at the time,
and they made that decision to purchase the
chassis, yeah.
And that was because that model was going out of production or something like that,
so it was now or never. At the time, the next generation project had already
begun, and we'd had the 47 tranche one trucks.
Mm-hmm.
There had never been talk that I can read of, of a tranche two
of the MAN until then. Was it just a reactionary
decision by, at that time? Oh, someone, "Look, there's
30, let's grab it." Or was it a considered, actually this is part of the
strategic plan that we have to build up our type three?
Well, certainly when
I look back at the records of that time, it shows that
the
decisions that were made under those operational pressures weren't really supported
by sufficiently strong procurement processes.
It wasn't supported well around the documentation,
whether there was good prototype gaps, gates in place for those, the
contract management. So right through the process, we've looked at those and
seen there are a lot of things that could've been done better as an
organization. The actual thinking behind
that decision,
it's hard to tell from that time, but I'd say looking back, it would appear
that the ability to expedite
by buying another big block of those-
Yeah
... appliances seems to be one of the major drivers between-
I understand that, and in the interest of time, I'll skip through.
But obviously SEM had been engaged with tranche one.
Mm-hmm.
And therefore, they ended up getting a contract in
2021 to build a prototype. And as you've told us,
AngloCo effectively cold called you
and made an un- I think you'd call it an unsolicited proposal to
make a prototype for tranche two. Is that correct?
That's what the records show, yes.
Yeah. So,
you ultimately select AngloCo, and I'm just going
off your fleet timeline here that was provided for our March
hearing.
Mm-hmm.
So is this correct? It says in September 2022, Fire and
Emergency orders from AngloCo a trial appliance to be
built on a MAN cab chassis that Fire and Emergency
already owns. Is that correct?
In 2022?
Right.
Sorry, can you just repeat that?
Yeah. Well, the fleet says that you order a trial appliance from AngloCo in
September 2022.
Hmm.
Gerald, do you want to talk to that just while I think?
Could I refer you to pages 54 and 55 of our submission?
You can.
Please. So the bottom of-
Specifically paragraph 5.54 perhaps?
Great. Starting 5.5-
Yes
... yeah, so that's-
So this one was wrong. Was it? The one that you provided for our March hearing.
Because the fleet timeline, happy to provide a copy, but specifically said, it
says September 2022, but that's wrong, is it?
I'm just trying to get the dates right. It's actually...
What date is it actually? It's-
So-
September 2021?
Sorry, could I refer you to paragraph 5.59?
Yes.
And 5.60.
So those, and 5.61, those are the
dates.
So those ones are correct, not the other ones that we've been provided. Okay.
So when
did AngloCo...
It says in 5.54 that they started to build a body in
July 2021. Is that correct?
So in paragraph 5.59, it says that we
shipped a MAN cab chassis to AngloCo for the
prototype build in late 2021.
In late 2021.
So can I refer you to paragraph 5.59?
Yes.
Please.
Yeah. I'm reading that. So-
And then, sorry, can I refer to paragraph 5.61,
which
documents when the completed prototype arrived in New Zealand,
which was December 2022.
Yeah. Okay. So,
on page 51 though in paragraph 5.27,
I just want to get these dates correct.
It says,
I just want to make sure we're getting this right, that AngloCo was selected in
July 2021.
5.27, is that?
Which one? I-
Sorry, I'll come
back to you. Okay, so
you're saying September is the correct date that they were selected and one was
sent over?
But the con-- so that's actually before SEM
get their contract in November 2021.
And that's in your post-hearing questions numbers 11 and 15.
I'm just trying to understand-
I'm just trying to get the right dates for you, so
Yeah. I'm just trying to understand, because it looks like SEM got their contract
in November 2021. They've been working with you since April
2020.
AngloCo, it looks like, rang up in July 2021, said,
"We'll make one for you," and in September had a contract signed.
So can I again refer to paragraph
5.40?
Yes.
Through to 5.47. So that sets
out in our written submission-
Yeah
... the engagement and the dates with SEM.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah.
So that is correct, in April '20, but they didn't get their contract until
November 2021.
The second stage, the full build.
So there was an initial design piece with SEM.
Yes.
That's correct.
Yeah.
And then secondly, once that design piece had completed, they were engaged to
build a prototype.
Yeah, correct. And that would be the November 2021 point when they got the full
contract. Is that right?
So in paragraph 5.48, the second stage
commencing in January 2021 involved formally engaging
SEM via a direct sourced approach to build a
Type 3 MAN prototype appliance.
Okay. So with that, ultimately,
though, you went with AngloCo and the reason that you
select AngloCo
is
because their trial appliance was meant to arrive
in
early
2022. It was meant to arrive in February 2022,
but it doesn't arrive until December. Is that correct?
This is the AngloCo trial appliance.
So the AngloCo trial appliance, so this is paragraph 5.61,
arrives in December '22.
Yes.
Undergoes acceptance testing
that occurred during February to March 2023.
Yeah.
And then there was further operational testing conducted-
In May
... in May 2023.
Right. So it turns up, what's that?
Ten months late, and then it gets tested the following year
in February and March. Some documents say just February, some say February
and March, but I assume it's late February, early March, something like that.
Well, can I refer you to-
Yes
... paragraph 5.61 in our written submission.
Yeah. Your post-hearing
question for the last one, number 20, said February only, but number 19 says
February and March. So yep, let's go with that.
When was the
decision made to go with AngloCo and agree to a
contract with them?
So paragraph 5.64.
Yes.
The procurement plan was produced in February 2023.
Right. So
I just want to understand this. The truck arrives in the country in December
2022.
It is tested in February and March 2023, just for
acceptance testing, and then the operational testing takes place in May
2023. But back in February,
you've already produced the direct source
contract with AngloCo.
A procurement plan.
Procurement plan.
So clearly from the documents, the planning was underway.
So the decision was made before you even tested it.
The procurement plan has been prepared.
And in March, am I not correct that in March it was delegated to
the CE?
So paragraph 5.65-
Yes
... is this what you're referring to?
It was delegated authority to the CE in March '23.
That's what the record shows, correct.
So at this point, SEM trial appliance hasn't even turned
up in the country, has it?
The one that's been in the pipeline to some degree since April
2020,
and effectively AngloCo rang up and
said, "We'll build you one." It turns up 10 months late.
We haven't even done the acceptance testing, and we're pretty much on short
finals to
buy 28 of them.
So you're correct. So paragraph 5.52 would show that the SEM
prototype does not arrive until June 2024.
So I'm just trying to understand this
bit where we are making a decision without even testing
the AngloCo trial appliance.
Is that
normal?
No, that's not normal. And like I said earlier, it
is obvious looking back at those things that
the decisions made under the operational
pressures of
ensuring that there was Type 3s coming into the system
certainly could've had stronger procurement aspects to them
through there. And to some degree, that's caused delays
in the longer term by not putting the rigor at that time.
I mean, but it was-
It was 10 months late at the very start, even just the trial appliance.
Mm-hmm.
That must raise some alarm bells, doesn't it?
Yeah. The
organization accepts that the
rigor at that time wasn't actually applied, and our focus is
actually on dealing with the long tail and the legacy of that,
making sure that we can get the trucks operational, but making sure more
importantly, that going forward, that the learning from that
is applied so that it doesn't end up in the same position.
But, there was no rigor, effectively is what it looks like.
There's a thing that says it went through and met
rigorous testing requirements, but then it turned out that a whole bunch of stuff
didn't work, like the RFI issue, radio frequency interference.
Deck monitors not working. We already knew at this point that there are issues with
the intercooler on the tranche one.
I assume there's likely that could happen on tranche two.
In fairness, you provide a pretty robust
list of the faults that have been found.
But we didn't even have a chance, did we, if we're not even testing that stuff
before we go and buy 28 of them?
And like I say, we've tried to be upfront with the
committee around what we've found and what we've discovered from those decisions at
the time. And yes, the organization could have
applied some stronger rigor over that period of time.
But we're very much focused on how we ensure that that doesn't happen
again, and we have the rigor in our processes through that.
Because it says the rear axle weight was tight to limits, but testing wasn't
conducted while fully loaded. So if it's tight to limits not
fully loaded, and we haven't even tried to fully load it.
This is
paragraph 5.71.
"The comprehensive acceptance testing regime for the prototype
showed full compliance across a wide range of criteria,
yet later evidence demonstrates that significant defects still emerged and
required correction after those tests had been completed."
So either fundamentally our wide range of criteria and our
comprehensive testing regime are fundamentally flawed, or we
just haven't done it.
Sup from Mike.
Okay.
Thank you.
5.01 in your submission. It
talks about you actually going overseas,
to develop and test alternative appliance type three designs,
eventually selecting SEM and AngloCo.
I'm just wondering, what was the date when you went overseas?
Because I'm just reading through this, it looks like that you've gone out and found
AngloCo, but obviously previously said that
No
... approached you. So I'm just trying to work out what date
that happened.
So just to clarify, if I may, around SEM and AngloCo.
So Fire and Emergency approached SEM, AngloCo approached Fire and
Emergency. So that's what the record shows, documentation
shows.
Okay. So this is not quite correct in this
5.01 where you say that you've actually been forced to go overseas to look for
something.
SEM is based in Australia.
I was talking about AngloCo.
Okay.
And in 5.65,
you talk about obviously doing a final approval for
28 Man AngloCo type three appliances,
which is quite a significant decision.
What, circa $30 million,
I assume. And that was done through an out of cycle board process.
And I'm just curious about actually what that process looks like to
actually make a decision
around $30 million.
Do you have any idea how that process is done for out of cycle
board decisions?
Not here today. We'd have to go back and have a look at that and then bring that
back to you.
Do you mean in general terms?
Yes, for this-
Out of cycle
... out of cycle.
Like is it just done through email, or do they have to have another meeting?
Because
clearly at this point of time, there's been some significant issues with the
procurement of type three. And then you make an
out of cycle board decision that's going to
procure another 28 type three appliances with significant
cost. And I'm just wondering actually what that process
looked like, because I would've thought if I was a board member, I'd be a little
bit cautious about making big decisions given the actual history of
type three.
Yeah. That's a valid
question and, I don't want to mislead the committee, and we'd need to go back and
have a look. Out of cycle
board decisions can range from the board
coming together to have a special meeting, to having an email,
approval process, to having a
discussion at a meeting and then signing that letter.
So I'm not sure which one of those processes,
and
we can come back to you with what that looks like.
Okay, we've got moving to Andy Foster now on the
screen.
Yeah. Well, thank you. Just going back to the overview
of the fleet that you got, and we are focusing at the moment on type three.
So you've got
in one place, you've given us 196 vehicles in your fleet, and
another place in your asset management plan, 206.
Why the difference? And does that mean you've actually had a number of
vehicles removed from service in that period of
time?
Because I think the asset management plan predated the later information you gave
us.
Yeah.
So I have 196 from the asset management plan
Okay, because you've got in
the asset management plan, it says there's 206 at one point.
Are you referring to the page?
Yep. It is page...
That's very helpful, they're not numbered.
It's under 3.2 fleets asset summary.
So Type 3 fire appliances, 206.
You're correct, there's 196.
It may have been a timing matter between the asset management plans
and the information provided to the committee
in the May hearing.
So which one-
We'd have to go back and clarify that.
So which one is-
But it's 196 at the moment.
It's 196. Okay, have we got 10 which have been retired
or a net 10 which have been retired in that period of time?
Didn't he try new?
We'll clarify.
We'll have to clarify that with you.
That would be very helpful. Given that we're focused on fleet and particularly
Type 3 and aerials,
I'm disappointed that you can't tell me why that trajectory's happened. Okay.
So I'll go back. Let's start with the 196,
20 year life cycle. You should be replacing roughly how many per year
then? I
can do maths, but I'd get you to do it for me.
Andy, can I suggest that you just hold that till we get to
procurement?
It is about Type 3, specifically about Type 3. It's about the fleet.
Okay. It's just that we hadn't quite finished where we were.
I thought you had a supplementary, that was all.
Oh, well, I thought you were going to me for a substantive, but-
Oh, sorry.
Look, carry on then at the moment, but we might-
Okay. Well, I don't-
Just indicating we might come back.
Well, look, where I'm going with this is,
and I'll give you the answer. Obviously, you should be replacing 10 a year, roughly
speaking. You've replaced 10 in the entire existence,
according to your own data, you replaced 10 in the entire existence of FENZ
operation.
How do you explain that? I know you've had problems with procurement, but that just
looks, you're going backwards at a great rate of knots, and
the age of the fleet, the Type 3 fleet, is
getting older very fast as well.
You can't blame now, surely
you can't blame now what you inherited, because that's almost 10 years ago.
We're not
trying to
blame what we inherited through there.
The tale of the Type 3s
does go back before Fire and Emergency, but the
ability to actually
procure and deliver the Type 3s certainly sits there over the
10 year of the life cycle and
I think the submissions have gone into quite a bit of detail around
what some of those challenges have been,
and why some of those
timelines are longer than anyone would've liked or
programmed through there.
But-
Given that you're currently-
Focus actually on getting it moving forward
... given that you're currently replacing at one tenth of the rate that you
should be according to your own asset management and life cycle plans, how are you
going to turn that around?
And actually, you've got to do more than that because you actually got more than
half of your Type 3 fleet is now over the age target.
So the asset management plan sets out a
replacement program of 122 Type
3 appliances from 2026/27 through to
2035/36. That won't
bring the entire Type 3 fleet 100%
within its target life, but it will bring it
86% within its target life by the year
2035/36. That's the plan.
That's 2026/27 to 2035-
/36
... /36. That's over, so nine years worth is that we're talking about there?
Correct.
So you are slightly ahead of the game on that one then,
because you should be replacing about 90 in that period if you're just holding
static.
That's correct. So the asset management plan-
So you get-
Plan 2022. Yes.
Okay, so you're getting a small gain.
Now, the other thing which we heard earlier in the hearings was the
mix of where you're spending your capital money.
And I think we got a pretty much 20%, 20%,
20% across
fleet, across buildings, across equipment, across
IT.
And is tempted to ask questions about IT, because it doesn't seem the IT system,
certainly for
the vehicle side of it, is much
use in terms of actually giving you a good picture of what's going on.
It's all being done manually. That's what all your firefighters are telling us.
Is that balance of where you're spending the money the right
balance?
Happy for me to take this, Susan?
Yes.
So that balance will change with the asset management plans.
So again,
this time moving out one year short of the 35/36, but to
34/35 the balance will be quite different across the
classes. And just to clarify, when I'm talking ICT,
I'm talking both CapEx and operating expenditure because software as a
service accounting treatment means that some of the
capital-like spend on ICT
is actually recurring the operating statement.
But at the end of year 34/35, we expect to have
27% on fleet, 4% on equipment,
16% on ICT, and 53% on property. But for
each year, going through to 2034/35,
the percentages will differ because they're determined by the asset management
plans going forward.
That's very sensible. That's an enormous amount of property compared to-
That is, and we do have some real challenges in property.
Hmm. I think it'd certainly be good to understand that all better,
but, Madam Chair, I'm sure you want to carry on focusing specifically on-
Yeah. Thank you, Andy. And can I move to Lamogna
now? Thank you.
Thanks, Madam Chair. And I probably will just suck mine onto the last
group of questions around the type threes.
What I wanted to understand was,
does the CE believe that with more
rigor, that you've got the
percentages right? Because I'm just referring to documents that
have been filed. I think it's paragraphs, I've got here
5.20, 5.21, 22, 23, and it's more about the
body cracking issues impact on service and ongoing
remediation. What I'd like to ask, um, Fenwicks is
that,
is the planning moving forward and going on what
you've just explained to Andy's question, do you have the
percentages right? Have you got the appropriate, um,
understandings of the fire,
um, type threes
fit for purpose? And will that be
suitable in terms of the fleet management going forward for the next
decade? Because you've talked about a decade, but then you've also talked about a
five-year plan for the opening comments of the chair.
Yes.
The question's directed to me.
I think, yes. I believe that the settings are right
and, um, we are needing to balance across
the asset portfolio.
The movement from one
part of the asset portfolio to another, um, creates pressures in that area as
well, just like any organization, um, and making sure we've got those
settings wrong. But I think the asset management plans clearly give us a detailed
plan of where the investment needs will be
going forward through the next 10 years.
Like I said earlier on, that will be informed
as the work from FOC develops to actually have a
clearer picture of the operational needs and requirements and the
changing needs of those and sitting across the
fleet strategy once we're able to pull that together.
My other question is with regards to, thank you for that, is around the cracking.
So we'd seen quite recently that there was a whole fleet
of fire engines that were brought into the assets.
Mm-hmm.
I visited in Hamilton where they got two specific new
fire trucks, but one was on the road for one day.
So how does the
executive team explain when you've got a promise of all
these new fire trucks and you've done all the data behind it, et cetera,
will there be the guarantee that when you do get new fleet that it will
service and it won't have all of these problems that you've had and that have been
listed?
Yeah, thank you. It's really important in
a organization that has critical gear like ours, like
the critical fleet, that when things are identified
as not 100%, that we actually
take a deliberate decision to ensure that we understand what the
problem is, we rectify the problem, and then we put it back into order.
So, that is the right thing to do rather
than leave them on the run until potentially they
fail there. So when we're talking about the appliances that were
put onto the run and then we took them off the run again, that was a
deliberate, um, and erring on the side of caution
decision to remove them to ensure that we can
address any issues that come out of them to make sure that they're going to
be resilient and safe for our people to operate in.
It's really tempting to get pressured
by
public timelines that we've committed to publicly, but we need to
make sure for the sake of our firefighters, um, that our
appliance is
robust and ready to operate when they go onto the run.
So, it was a deliberate decision to move that.
It was a deliberate decision on the
side of caution, um, and it is about understanding what the problems
are or what the issues are, finding the rectification for that,
testing those, and then putting them back into service.
Thank you. Tim.
So I just want to come back to this selection of AngloCo.
5.27B it is the one I was looking for before, where it
says,
"One prototype appliance was designed and built by AngloCo.
The build of this appliance was commenced around June 2021."
That just can't be correct because on paragraph 5.59,
we shipped the chassis-
Yeah
... to AngloCo
in late 2021. I don't equate that with June 2021.
Okay. So it's probably just wrong. Okay.
So
I guess the questions are because SCM, we understand you're doing
some work with them to try and fix tranche one.
They effectively never come through with anything, right?
Because their trial appliance doesn't even turn up and then, so yeah, okay.
And
the solution produced by Fraser Fire and Rescue
ultimately fixes tranche one? That
has worked out? Or is it the one by the other local manufacturer that's referred
to?
Oh, the rectification of the cracking.
Yeah. The physical rectification was done by Fraser Fire and Rescue, is that
correct?
That's my understanding.
Yeah, okay. So SEM,
a week ago, it didn't work out. We've gone with AngloCo,
who are also in the middle of the next generation project at the
time and are one of the two suppliers that are shortlisted
for that.
But the other one, Emergency One, aren't invited and in paragraph
560,
you talk about, "In undertaking this procurement process, FENZ recognized the
importance of maintaining separation from the ongoing next generation Type
3 procurement focus. No other suppliers from next
generation were asked to submit a proposal."
Tell me if I'm understanding this correctly, you're saying, "Hey, we've got this
next generation thing, so we're not going to invite Emergency One or anyone else
that has tended for
next generation, because we want some distance between the two." And yet at the
same time, you've got AngloCo, who are the only other successful
supplier,
that are now getting...
Even if we take that June date as correct, they cold call you in July.
In September, there's a trial appliance
accepted, and
a
cab sent to the UK.
And
then they're getting a contract signed before testing's done.
I
can understand why people are raising concerns, but it looks
like someone, maybe through next generation, has got a nice relationship with
AngloCo and is going, "Well, these guys are good.
We'll just get them in
because we haven't gone to anyone else."
Can you help us to understand how you're thinking and arriving at that, sir?
So my review of the documentation around AngloCo at this
time was that AngloCo, in undertaking their due diligence for
the next generation proposal-
Yep
... came across the
Tranche one 47 MAN appliance cracking issue
through their due diligence search.
And as a result of that,
proactively reached out to Foreign Emergency and said,
"We think we can design a body build that will work on the MAN
chassis." So that's my understanding from the documentation I reviewed.
Okay.
So of the 28, we know that 16 have
arrived and have been accepted.
The other 12, is the issue mechanical?
Is it contractual?
What's happened to the other 12?
The other 12 that we're still waiting to receive?
Yes. Is the delay commercial or mechanical
with those?
We're working proactively with AngloCo around the next steps on those and
when we're likely to procure. Part of that will be a
staged
implementation of those, so-
Are they built yet?
They're in New Zealand, those 12.
So
that's my question, is what is the
issue with them? Is it a mechanical, is it that they haven't fixed the RFI or
there's a deck monitor issue, or is it a contractual hold-up
with AngloCo which is stopping them being released
into your acceptance?
There's a whole range of elements that sit in there, a little bit of
all of them that sit in there, and we want to make sure when we
accept those, that the things that we've discovered through
the
initial
ones that came on have been rectified
through the 12 before we accept them coming into the-
So is it FENZ
saying, "We're not willing to accept them yet," or is it AngloCo saying,
"You can't have them yet"?
We're in discussions with them from a commercial sense around those.
Certainly,
it's not something that I'm willing to go into in a public forum,
but if the committee wish to separate that, we can go into some of
the
negotiations we're having there.
Yeah, I'd be interested. Obviously, we can't do that now while we're in public.
It's deeper than the RFI issue. Has the RFI issue been
resolved? Because in the
information you've given, I've seen the RFI issue was found, obviously, after you
signed the contract for the 28, because we hadn't done the testing.
But then when you did do the testing, you found the RFI issue.
Mm-hmm.
Which, as I look at it, is just on the
A range, the FM frequency, not the UHF or the
VHF. And it needed a bespoke
solution that had to be done in the UK,
and yet we've got 16 of them, well, 28 of them in the country, but 16 that
have been accepted in New Zealand that haven't had that resolved.
One of the documents said it was 18 months away to fix.
Mm-hmm.
I'm just trying to understand
where that's at.
Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you. My understanding is that
the RFI issue has been resolved
for the
first 17,
is my understanding.
But that 17th is the trial one,
and that's not in use yet, is it?
Is it just the 16 that have come on, or has the trial appliance also been accepted?
I'm just going to refer to my notes.
No, that's fine.
AngloCo trial one.
It's the green sheet, sir.
Thank you, Pete.
Okay.
So if I refer you to the green sheet.
Yes.
If we go down the bottom, there's the
MAN AngloCo Type 3 prototype.
Right.
If you have a look at the reason for the outstanding
issues
Okay, so the RFI one is imminently to
be
resolved?
I can't see anything outstanding in that list that refers to
RFI.
Yeah. What I read from your report was that you're tracking for maybe September
this year was the best case, that it took
5.74D, said it was going to take 18 months to
resolve that issue. And
maybe September this year to have that, but the trucks could come on in the
meantime. But I think you've got the...
Is it the high-pressure deliveries creating some issues?
No.
I think it's best if we come back to you, so that we don't mislead the
committee at all around the
RFI issue and-
Okay
And now Mike has a sup on this.
Thank you.
Just curious, this is obviously quite an extended time period this has rolled out
over.
Yeah.
And trying to work out what was happening between, I guess, the
board and the CEO and the communication back and
forth.
Mm.
What type of instructions were you getting from the board or direction from the
board as this was unrolling?
The board was certainly
mindful of the time that it was taking,
and looking to ensure that we were
expediting the process as quickly as possible.
But they also understood some of the challenges that we were going
through,
as far as
what we've articulated through the submission.
Were they supportive of what was happening, what you were doing?
Certainly the board were,
like I was, frustrated at the length of time that this was taking and the
impact that this has on our current fleet.
And there was a real strong focus on
how do we make sure that
we can expedite the process as fast as we could through there.
But a big sense of frustration at the time.
And like I said,
the tale of this goes a long way back, and we're dealing with
the decisions and things that were made where,
in hindsight, if more rigor had been put across by the organization, that we
may not have the same challenges that we're having now with those.
Yeah. I guess I'm just curious. It has
dragged on for a long time, and it seems to be issue after issue.
Mm.
And I'm just trying to work out between, I guess, management and the
board,
what actions, I guess, were getting,
I guess, put to the management from the board to ensure things could
actually move forward
at a better pace, I guess, or to a point that actually we're getting
these appliances in and received and actually operational.
And so I'm just struggling to work out what was happening
between the board and management over that period of time.
And like I said, there were certainly discussions and
direction to me around the need to
expedite the process as much as we can, but
also awareness that we need to ensure that we get these
appliances right.
Where do you think the accountability falls for these errors?
I think ultimately, these
fall back to the initial
rigor that was put around the process.
The genesis of this goes right back to 2014,
when the initial
cabin chassis design was
put in place, and which obviously, over the period
of time, we saw the body build on those cracking.
But that goes right back to those early times, so I think-
Do you not think, as the CEO, some of that falls onto you, though, the
accountability of it?
I think my role is to ensure that
we deal with those issues as they come through appropriately, and
that we have an eye on continuous improvement and making sure that we can
rectify the challenges that we see as we
experience.
Okay. That brings us to the end of that block, but it may
be that we come back to some, because this seems to be
the main area. But we are moving now on, as our
schedule says, to aerial appliances.
So I'm just going to check if you had
anything to say about that first. I don't think you ever thought you'd hear it.
You're
okay to go straight to questions?
Yes. I was just going to say that
the aerials are a critical
specialty capability,
and that
when there's local outages, when they occur,
that they shouldn't be dismissed.
But also the national network and
the relief appliances, they're a mitigation
and not the solution. They're a mitigation that sits in there that the organization
applies.
But we are running a balance of,
internationally, all fire services have the same challenge around
the you can't have every resource at every station across the
country, and what's the right balance in our cities.
Thank you. And I'll start with Tim.
Thank you. So
just so I've got this right, there's four Type 5s and one Type 6 on order.
Mm-hmm.
When are they due for delivery?
Thank you.
So we have them scheduled at the moment,
delivered
in the quarter three of 26/27.
Mm-hmm.
That means they'll go through the green process of acceptance testing, et
cetera.
So they'll start that acceptance testing early next year. Is that...
Okay, so
in July 2025, the asset management plan says that
the aerial appliances have had their final inspections completed,
and when shipped to New Zealand, Fire Emergency will take ownership of them.
Is
that correct?
So we
have yet to complete the final
operational
inspections. So there's different inspections
along the contractual dates.
And as you progress through the build, you do inspections of the build
to date, similar to if you were building a house.
I imagine that's a good correlation.
Yes.
And there's some
inspection scheduled in Brisbane for the five heavy
and the six,
that's coming up over the next
month to two months.
Okay. But it does say in your asset management plan, and I'm
probably, I'm in the details here, but it's footnote 39 on page
42, and it says, "These appliances have had their
final inspections completed."
And that's after the sentence that says, "The large type five is going to Parnell
Station and the type six is going to Hamilton." Footnote 39, "These have had their
final inspections completed." But now you're saying they've still got more
inspections to be completed.
Yeah. It's a complex build, so all we've been doing is things-
But there can only be one final one, can't there?
So, the footnote refers to these appliances had their final inspections
completed-
Yes
... when they are shipped to New Zealand.
Yes.
Fire Emergency will officially take ownership of them. So.
Correct. But it does say that they have had, past tense, their final inspections
completed, and that document came out in July 2025.
Mm-hmm.
So a year ago, they had had their final inspections
completed. Now we're doing some more inspections.
That's incorrect because before we take ownership of those
vehicles, we need to do our final acceptance inspections.
So they hadn't been, had they been built a year ago?
They weren't complete a year ago.
Okay. I feel like you're dancing around that one. Well, let's go back a step.
When did the delivery phase begin?
So the delivery?
Mm-hmm. Yes, the delivery phase.
We're expecting in quarter three,
26/27.
Right. But-
That's on page 81 of your booklet.
Okay. If I go to
paragraph 719
of your submission for this on aerial appliances, it
says, "In 2024, the project moved into the delivery
and design phase."
Mm-hmm.
So that's not physical delivery, that's what, that's because design phase is
pretty
fundamentally the start, isn't it?
The design phase is at the start of the process.
Right. So, it says it moved into the delivery phase,
delivery and design phase in '24, so that's not delivery.
I'm just trying to work out where it's at because it says the delivery phase
started in '24, that says they had their final inspection a year ago.
But it also says that in November last year,
there are still design changes happening.
I mean, it's like we're kind of
designing the
plane, the appliance as we build. We're already
into that delivery phase and we're still making design changes.
They'd had their final, is the issue that they'd had their final
inspection, but then we changed the design and so we now have to do
changes and now there's more inspections and...
But I'm trying to understand what the delay is from a final
inspection in a year ago
to sitting here today.
Mm-hmm.
Carrying on with that sentence, it talks about the
at this stage, the steering committee's attention shifted to
ensuring the appliances would meet fire and emergency operational regulatory needs
in practice.
That has certainly been one of the
things that's come through
around ensuring that we have the
all those different elements in the procurement around the operational
needs, around the technical needs, all aligned,
as part of the process. So, that is moving forward,
getting greater alignment between all the different components,
to ensure they're in place. But the submission
clearly shows there that,
the attention was shifted to ensuring
the appliances would meet the fire and emergency's operational needs.
Okay. But I'm
still not hearing the reason why after a final inspection a year ago,
they're not ready now and they're still at least six months away
from physically arriving and being able to even start acceptance testing, let alone
the rest of the process to become, to get out on the run.
Yeah. So do you want to talk about the current status of that?
Sure. So, 7.26 and 7.27 I
think tells you the current status.
So-
Yeah
...
what you'll find is we've got outstanding issues since November
25 that we're clearing.
And we've been using
operational response experts in these vehicles to help in the
resolution of those outstanding issues.
The final inspection has, and
acceptance has not been completed today.
Okay. So I understand that, but it's not actually telling me anything.
What is the, like what has happened?
Something has happened since July last year.
Sure.
I can give you an example-
Yeah
... without going into any technical.
The weight of vehicles is always a consideration.
I know there was a period of time that operational response was
asked to see if we could move piping to help alleviate
that issue. I had the expert aerial
trainers consult on that, and we decided that that
wasn't a solution. We looked at whether we could reduce
equipment. So all of these considerations are done with
operations to help resolve an issue that's been identified
during the build.
Mm.
That's just one example for you.
Can I just
ask my
acting DCE for assets to come forward to the table too?
Absolutely.
Can I be able to-
Sure. Yeah
... get into quite some detail, I might be able to give a little bit more-
Yeah, yeah, absolutely
... more amount of detail to that. Mm-hmm.
And while you're coming forward, Andy or Lamonga, are yours subs or
primaries?
Are they subs?
Well, it depends. I mean, Tim's going well into procurement issues, so
on that basis, I can probably say yes.
You want to do that too. Fair enough.
Yeah, well, might as well. You said we'd leave-
Okay
... leave procurement till the end, why not?
I'll come to you soon.
Okay.
You.
Sorry.
Go for it.
Did you have anything to add on the aerials?
No, I think just picking up on
Megan's point, issues such as waiting, configuration
considerations has added a delay.
I think in terms of looking to the submission where it refers to the move
into delivery and design phase, perhaps unhelpful in here, but it's
project management language. It wasn't meaning delivery
physically handing over. So as of today,
three of the Type 5, so the Type 5 mediums are with Fraser Fire
Rescue, where they're working on their
work program.
We have one Type 5 heavy and a Type 6
with
the producer over in Australia. So they are all still
with the builders.
But are we having a commercial issue where,
I don't know, Fiins won't pay whoever the contract's with overseas, and they're not
paying the subcontractor, and therefore, someone's holding something back.
Are there those kind of issues that are delaying this?
I'm not sure. I've literally stepped into the role.
This is my first week-
Do you know?
... so need to-
Are there commercial issues that are holding this up?
One of the
changes in the process with the aerials was having a turnkey approach.
Well, not turnkey, but having a single contractor-
Yeah
... manage the contract.
Yeah.
Certainly,
we're managing those contracts carefully.
And again, I'm happy to talk to the committee in a closed thing around
that.
Okay.
That's all I've got on the Type 5s.
Thank you. Mike.
Thank you.
Just
wondering, currently, and I think you touched on it at the very start of this
session around the
Type
5, Type 6, and there's 10, is
that all right?
Is it the same number there was in 2017
in
.
Sorry, I've got
one more. Yeah. Thank you.
I would have to go back and verify the number
at 2017, but we've currently got
six Type 5 and four Type 6.
Yeah. Okay. Then I guess my question is,
because obviously since 2017, there's been a lot of growth in New
Zealand.
Are you certain that number's an appropriate number
now in 2026?
And
should it be actually higher than that?
I think the work that we're doing in FOC is going to really
define that. I need it to be data-driven and evidence-based to
actually verify where we should have those resources.
We have an inherited layout of fleet, and I think
it's the right time for us to review that and see that we
do have the right mix of appliance types.
Okay. So I guess
when you haven't done that work,
there's potential issues with your budgeting moving forward because your budget
moving forward is just based on the exact same number, is it?
The asset management plan's based on a like for like.
Yes.
So there could be, although you're saying at the moment you've got a
$154 million gap-
Mm-hmm
... it could be a lot more considering actually you haven't reviewed if you have
the right number of appliances across the
country.
It could be more, it could be less. Like Megan said, it's
actually looking at what that work produces so that we've got an accurate
picture of it rather than speculating against it.
But-
But the asset management plans are based on a like for like.
Last question. I just noticed on the Type 4s, there's 19.
And there's only two relief Type 4s.
Is that an issue with only having two
relief ones? A lot of our ones have, I guess, a bigger percentage of relief.
Is there a concern there with having two
relief Type 4s?
I think we have a fleet that we've inherited.
I think the Type 4 project is underway.
I think some of the Type 4s
are sitting in locations where they're not used a lot.
Ideally, you'd probably want to look at the mix when
we look at the whole fleet,
but it currently is the fleet that we have.
Okay. Thank you. Lamonga.
Thank you.
Mike asked one of my questions, so I'll go straight into it.
In terms of,
two things, in terms of- ... procurement, design,
operational requirements, and regulatory constraints.
Do you think you've got a current stock?
Do you think moving forward, even in your five-year plan,
that you have got ample supply of the aerial
appliances, given that there's urban sprawl, and that
continues in terms of housing and communities, et cetera?
And also the type. Is there a conversation that continues
with the likes of IE local councils?
Because what we've heard on the ground and what I've heard in urban is
that some of the appliances, and I'm looking at the aerials that you've
currently got, actually can't get into some of the streets given the urban
sprawl. So,
given that Mike's asked an earlier question of my questions, can you
comment on that?
I think that's a really good question and, it's one of
the importance of having that, both the future
operating capability, but also this fleet strategy to allow
those things to be taken into account.
Because
if we were to buy a whole lot more aerial appliances and then find that
we couldn't deploy them operationally because of the constraints of the size of
streets and access,
well then, we've defeated the purpose.
So there's a number of different components that need to come into that wider
piece of thinking as to how we deploy
our different tactical approaches.
And what does that mean for
our
current like for like stock? Do we need to make changes in there?
They're some of the questions that we'll need to grapple with as an organization
when we have a better idea of
all of the different drivers that will drive our capability going forward.
And just quickly, is your rigor
the capabilities? Are you getting that information
fed into your system so that you can pivot when you have to
because you've got budgetary constraints, budgetary
requirements, you are trying to plan a
year ahead so that you've got the correct amount of fleet to
respond to the emergencies that are being brought
forward on a daily basis?
Yeah, that's certainly the
value of the network of approaches.
So at any given time, making sure that we can provide an appropriate
response.
And that doesn't mean we'll always have the
desired resource that we'd always want.
If we have multiple fires at the same time, can't
split trucks, especially specialist trucks like aerial and two to be at two
different positions. So, there's a balance of how
much
risk we can afford and carry as an organization when
appliances are deployed.
But the network approach allows us to
respond appropriately to the different calls of service that we have across New
Zealand.
Thank you.
Thank you. And coming to you, Andy.
Yeah, thank you. Look, just wanted to check, first of all, because you've used
different terminologies in different places.
You've got, as I understand it, 28
type four, five, six
vehicles.
That's according to your asset management plan.
29 in the inquiry submission in May.
Okay. Look, that's close enough anyway. Let's stick with 29 then.
How many have you replaced, because you've used different terminology about special
vehicles and so on, how many have you replaced in the
almost decade that FENZ has been operating?
Of the aerials?
Yeah.
None at this point.
Okay. Right. Cool.
What I wanted to ask you then is the, because I can see them aging, but what I
wanted to ask you then is your
process of procuring replacements for these.
Ravin, when you started the conversation, you talked about turnkey rather
than sort of specialist design of everything, which we seem
to do quite a lot of in New Zealand.
But I'm conscious that there are certain circumstances, too, that you're talking
about with
street environments which may be difficult for
these large vehicles to go down. To what degree can you do these
things as
turnkey as opposed to having to have
specialist designs for different circumstances?
And if I just off the one other thing, do you get any input?
Because most of the time in smaller streets,
mostly, I would think they're going to be smaller buildings as
well. But that may not always be true where you wouldn't
need the aerial appliances. But to what degree is that an issue?
Are you s- excuse me, are you seeking that response
from Kerry?
Well, I think, Ravin, you made the comment about trying to
buy things that are more turnkey, and it seems that one of the complexities
we've had in this whole fleet procurement process is
it feels like lots of things are being designed-
Yes
... specifically for New Zealand circumstances.
And I just really wanted to understand why we have to do that differently than
anywhere else, why our environment is different to anybody else's
anywhere else on the planet.
And we make life difficult for ourselves sometimes.
Yeah, those are very good questions.
So, my response,
I apologize, but my response will be based on my personal
experience rather than from FENZ because I haven't got the
background. But, I mean,
generally, you start off by saying, "Well, others have fire
appliances. They have fire appliances-" ... yeah. They're just next door.
So why is it that we can't just go and buy one of those
or something similar? That is the sort of the starting point.
Why-
We seem to do that for cars anyway. I know that it's much simpler, but, yeah.
Yes.
But I think the overall
response would be that we want fit for purpose
equipment that we can get hold of as quickly as
possible
so that we are not solving one
unacceptable situation by creating another one, which is what we've done
here.
So we
should be looking at our procurement and contractual
approaches that will give us the outcome in
the timeframe that we're seeking and with the confidence that
we're seeking and within the budgets that we're seeking.
Now, none of those are true here, so unfortunately this is not an
acceptable situation we've found ourselves
in. But to respond to your question, there would be certain
things that are peculiar. So I know from my other
experiences that
more and more
developers are building their subdivision where
they do not have to novate the
road network to the council, because the council roading
agency won't accept it because it's not of the right width.
And
similarly, the water entity, and I'm talking about
Auckland Council here, would not accept
a public fire hydrant in a private road.
So you have these
new
scenarios that are being created.
So those roadways are narrow. So they're narrow
for rubbish trucks, they're narrow for firefighting
trucks to get through.
Then you can look for other means of getting the same resilience,
because you want to save lives. And is it that these dwellings need
to have sprinklers because the firefighters wouldn't be able to get there?
So there's a broader approach to how do we save lives, at the
same time, increase resilience of communities, would be my
approach. As I said, this is my thinking, but
I can't respond on behalf of FENZ at this point in time.
So thanks, Ravindren. Kerry and your team, can you give us
a bit of a steer on that as well? Because it seems disturbing that
if we are doing developments in a way, and if that is the driver
and we're allowing developments to occur, which are
basically trying to do things on the cheap, somebody else is picking up the tab,
and in this case, it's you.
Yeah. Thank you. And there is a number of components that sit in there.
There's a balance between operational requirements and
which sometimes can drive bespoke
things for our designs
across New Zealand. And that's not to say that's right or wrong, but there's a
balance between that and buying off-the-shelf appliances.
Things like axle weights, the way that
other fire services operate them,
are all considerations in just being able to go and buy an
off-the-shelf appliance that need to be weighed up
because that then balances
against how do our firefighters actually use the appliances in the way that they
use them here, and how do we train them to operate differently?
But every time we put more bespoke
design elements into an appliance, what it creates is it
creates more risk that where the first time that
those appliances are being tested,
and tested as a whole system, that they actually work
and won't fail. So we need to work through those issues as we bring them on
board to make sure all those things are ironed out.
So
the approach of looking to how can we move to a
more turnkey type solution,
and what's the balance of that, that we lose as far as functionality and the way
that we operate, is certainly part of the consideration going forward
around our procurement. And that is, like I said before, how do we make
sure the operational requirements are really aligned closely with the
technical requirements and what's on the market as part of those procurement
approaches.
If I can just finish off that area, Chair,
because it feels like you've got effectively two
objectives which are in conflict.
One is the fit for purpose, which may have some variation
between a New Zealand environment and somewhere else.
Mm-hmm.
And opposed to that is the being able to get things on time.
Now, quite clear, you're way behind on
procurement of these as well. You should've replaced
about 9 of them, give or take.
No, sorry, not about 15 of them, give or take, and you've replaced
none in the period that FENZ has been operating.
And clearly the bespoke elements are causing you difficulties of actually
getting these vehicles, not just these ones, but all of them, commissioned.
I've got no idea how many people or
different companies manufacture fire appliances around the world,
but is there nobody who-- I'm getting a feeling that there's nobody who is
building fire engines which are acceptable.
And that doesn't mean you've tinkered with everything under the sun, but they're
acceptable and will do the job under New Zealand conditions so that you can
actually, A, buy them, and B, get them on
New Zealand roads and streets,
at a much greater rate than you're
quite self-evidently managing to deliver.
If I just look on your point around that, if I look at
the Type 1 and Type 2 procurements,
they've been relatively seamless in the procurement of those, and
the
responses from our people around the country is that it does fit those operational
needs, and we've got a repeatable
procurement process and design now that can be
rolled out and deployed through there.
The issue we have with the Type 3 is,
being able to define a repeatable design that will work for us, that
is not as bespoke as
it's
sometimes been in the past.
But very much,
the simpler we can make that, the less challenges we'll have with
our procurement, and the faster that we'll be able to deliver those.
But there are different requirements around the world
to
roading conditions and all those sort of things that mean
there's not,
to my knowledge anyway, one type of appliance that
suits all environments. Some of those roads in Europe, for instance,
they're tiny, they're small, and their appliances are quite,
in some parts,
really small in the way that they operate through there.
Right. Way smaller than ours.
Yeah. We need to keep moving because we're running-
Okay
... a bit behind. Sorry, I'm just going to move. Tim's got one quick question.
Quick Type 4 question. Because you've said your overall aerial availability is
99.72%, does that include when
someone like Palmy get their Type 4 called out,
and if it's not serviceable, I understand they take that call sign, let's say it's
214, and then just annotate a note, "No ladder," and
they respond in a Type 3,
would that still indicate that a 214 has responded, therefore
an aerial has responded?
Cool. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you for that question.
What we do is we actually change the call sign so we know
it's not a Type 4. So for example, it might be
214 is taken offline and we put
a Type 3 pumper in its place, and it's called a 213,
indicating it's a Type 3. In that example, that Type
3 will have our 464 ladder on it, which has a reach of
about 14 meters. That's replacing the 17
meters on the Type
4, and it gives a good capability. So both the Type
4, that's-
But will that indicate there's a aerial available in terms of your
99.72%?
No, because 213 actually is telling everyone it's a Type
3.
Yeah, so that won't be included in the 99.72%
of aerial availability if it's a 213 with the
special ladder?
I'm sorry, I'm not sure of your question.
Well, you're saying that 99.72% of the time you've had aerials
available.
Could you refer me to your page, please?
Yeah, page 22, paragraph 2.55.
You said 246 mechanical issues while appliances responded to
88,000 incidents, 98 breakdown from
alert to arrival, and therefore 99.72%
availability.
So that's while responding. So it will be-
Yeah, so if it's never going to respond and you're going to take 213 instead, it
won't indicate the fact that it's not capturing that, is it, that data?
No, because it's not on a run, so to speak.
Because it's never available. Right.
So they never get captured, so therefore it doesn't actually pick up the times
that the aerial
is available. I think there's no South Island relief Type 4 at the moment because
it's the one in Palmy.
But it won't capture that, will it?
Because it never responds, because it was never there to start with.
It would be captured in vehicles that are off the run,
for maintenance.
It will, but it won't be captured in those availability statistics.
In those figures, no.
Correct. Right. So 99.72 might be a bit generous if we were to
think about what's available for the run rather than what's available during the
response. Yeah.
Okay. We are running a little bit late, and I do want to give
people a five-minute break at least.
So
I'm giving you that break now, and we'll start back here at half past
on that clock. So if you have a look at that, I think it's running a bit
fast. Or slow, sorry.
Sorry, for you people, I think it's about a minute and a half, isn't it?
No, it's been on here. You've got five minutes.
It must be my clock.
So no, my clock says 2:27.
Oh. Yeah.
Finished?
No, it's a break. What?
Tough. What do you mean tough? They're asking tough
questions. Yeah.
How are they responding then?
A lot of
this is historical.
Oh, okay. To the current people,
we're not there.
Okay.
So what do you say?
You sort of have to say, "I wasn't there."
Like that. Ask me if
the board is the right composition. I don't know.
It's your board, how would you
know? Exactly. So it would be improper- Yeah ...
for me to make a judgment call against it.
Yeah, and they should accept it. Hmm.
It's a stupid question to ask anyway, because it's your one.
I think. It's a general question.
What they're saying is,
the question is saying
it's a question to the board who are not there.
Mm.
The ones who were there or are there now.
It's like, "Are you doing your job?"
Okay.
I'm going.
Whoever
was talking, you should mute.
Welcome
back.
We're now moving to other appliances, including Type 1,
Type 2, rural, white fleet, and brigade-owned.
Was there anything that you wanted to start with?
No? Ready to
go. Tim.
Can I just ask about the weight issue, because this applies to the white fleet.
I've heard examples from white fleet,
your lines rescue guys hitting weight issues when they're in a fully loaded
4x4, but you've also referred to it in terms of aerial appliances.
And I think your Type 3, which only just made the weight limit, was on the
rear axle but it wasn't fully loaded.
Have you formally requested an exemption to axle weight
limits from NZTA?
On our white fleet? Across the board, on wherever it's
needed. Particularly,
you've said it's an issue for
your heavy appliances as well. Mm.
Jim, do you want to talk to them about the-
Yeah. So,
in the past, we have on a case-by-case basis approached for
exemptions with regards to the aerials.
For the Type 6, the supplier is
managing
that process, both in terms of dimensions and also the weight.
That's part of their contract arrangement.
We're going to be picking up responsibility for what we call the Type
5 heavy. We're in the process at the moment of engaging a third
party to assist us with all our weight exemption application
processes.
Because I heard examples in Auckland of
one of the aerials having to refuel to get to the Woodgrove fire just
to stay within weight limits, maybe carrying 150
instead of 400 liters in the reservoir that they
might carry because of weight limits.
I just wrote to the minister straight away and said, "Hey, can't we just give them
a blanket exemption?" There's one for concrete trucks, there's one for cranes.
Surely we want to give one to our first responders.
Mm. Have you just asked? Mm. Wouldn't that fix it? Mm.
And therefore enable some of these trucks as well that are coming off the shelf to
just roll out? Mm.
All I'm wondering is have you asked NZTA, and if not, can we? Mm.
I was going to say, I
know historically there's been some case-by-case applications.
Scope had one, didn't it?
But-
A blanket exemption, the old Scope?
I couldn't tell you.
Pretty sure it did. Yeah. Scope in Auckland. Yeah.
But we have engaged, or sorry, I can't say. We are engaging.
We've spoken to, we can't yet finalize the contract, a third party to
act on our behalf-
To support us, because that's their kind of-
You can't just go straight to NZTA and say, "Please, can we have an exemption?"
We certainly will engage directly with them, but we also want to bring in tech
collectives of somebody who this is what they do.
They work with other industries-
Okay
... to do those work exceptions.
Are we really?
There's no reluctance to ask for an exemption should we need an exemption.
Okay.
Keep going.
Oh, you were going on that.
No. If you want to tag an on.
I can just jump in.
Okay.
Just want to question around
issue type one. Is there,
I guess, a target average age that you want to achieve across the
fleet of type ones?
Yes. It's 25 years.
But if you have a whole fleet, what's your average age target, I guess?
Oh, I see what you mean.
Yeah.
Well, we're focused on and actually getting our
entire fleet within the average ages.
So,
20 years for the type threes,
and 25 years for the type ones and twos, and that's
basically on the,
I guess, the frequency of use or the workload that they're put under,
the difference between the two age groups.
So if I take that, then you'd want 100% of type ones
to be
within that 25-year age.
That's certainly our aspiration. Mm.
And so currently,
I'm just looking at the asset management plan.
There's 61% with the average age of 18.
Mm-hmm.
So obviously, there's still a significant amount that's not within that
100%.
So I'm just wondering, the focus for the first nine years was on
type one for one of the appliances, and we're still quite far off
that.
Mm.
Why are we so far away when that was one of the focuses?
And at the beginning of the session, you said the main
issue was type three.
Mm.
Basically, you wouldn't be here if it wasn't for type three.
This requirement wouldn't be happening.
But there's still other issues here when you look at this.
I'm just wondering-
Mm
... if all the investment was put into these spaces, why are we still
at 61% of that?
Hmm. And I think if you have a look at the
material that was supplied, it shows over that period of time, we've
effectively, for those types, maintained that.
Pretty much maintained the average age of it.
And so we haven't been able to materially move that over
that period of time, but we've certainly been able to maintain that as we've
brought other appliances into the fleet, like the tankers and things that we've
purchased in that.
So, the intention and the asset management plan is to take the type ones, in
particular, from 34% outside of target life in
'26, '27, through to 17% by
2035, '36. So it won't be all of the
appliances inside target age, but it's essentially halving it from where it
will be start of this year. So that's the asset management plan's intent for type
ones.
Mm-hmm.
The type twos will be all of those appliances 219 inside
target life by the end of that 10-year period
or that nine-year period. So that's the asset management plan's design.
Thank you.
A quick financial question, and then I just wanted to ask about brigade owned, but
I'll give you the... In your post-hearing questions from the hearing
in May, number nine was around the costs incurred for
leased vehicles where they exceed expected or agreed
replacement parameters.
The 2026 figure is roughly
140K.
That's an expense, a charge, not a rebate.
Am I reading that correctly?
So, it looks like a shared profit loss.
So it's a shared profit,
and maintenance and tires, so 139.
So is that a rebate or a charge? Does it cost you, or is that money
you got back?
If it's a shared profit loss and it's
not in brackets, then it's a shared profit.
So you got that amount of money back off your contract?
Sorry, no. So wrong way around. Excuse me. That looks like it's a cost, so 140.
Yeah, that's a cost, right?
Yeah. That's a cost, yeah.
The year before you got 37,000 back.
Yeah.
And is that just because, because I noticed that your policy has changed, you've
gone from 100,000 or three years for replacement to 150,000
in six years.
295 of the 580. So about half of your vehicles exceed that
policy. That's in questions two to seven.
It sort of steps us through that. But nine gives you the cost.
So is it
an intentional decision to, "Hey, we're better to stretch out these lease vehicles,
and yet they're a bit older and it's going to cost us money on the contract, but
it's saving us on a replacement." Or how are we ending up paying
140,000 for exceeding our
parameters?
So I don't know everything about the white fleet.
What I can say is that during the COVID period, 2020 to 2023,
the vehicles were very difficult to procure.
So some of those issues occurred because we had long wait times for
vehicles.
Mm-hmm.
So that's as much as I know.
And I accept that, but that's not the 2026 answer, is it?
Which is the standout.
That's not going to be a COVID issue in '26.
No.
Right.
Okay, well, then maybe just quickly on brigade owned.
In the submissions, I have got them all there, but we've had
some examples of brigades where they had a brigade-owned appliance, and they're
kind of feeling like they have to hide it because they don't want to lose it.
They're keeping it effectively as a spear.
There are other examples of brigade owned
Everything from jet skis for swiftwater rescue, which I think I've been
told in Waikato they can't use, through to your
4x4s in some remote areas to get into large parks, out onto beaches and stuff.
So that sounds quite pragmatic. Where are we at with that?
Because when we had the annual review hearing, I know there was a large discussion
around jet skis, swiftwater rescue.
Mm.
But where the brigade owns something, whether
it's an appliance, a jet ski, a buggy, or whatever it might be, are they able
to use it, or are they going to have that taken off them?
Do they need to be feeling like they need to hide stuff?
Or
where's the line of pragmatism versus responsibility?
Yeah. So if I just start on the jet skis.
And it's good to be in a position now where
Ngāruawāhia and Huntly, which were the ones with the jet skis-
Yes
... in the most,
have decided to make up a separate entity,
so a local solution to a local issue that sits in there.
But on the wider scale of that,
when we're talking about different capabilities and when we're talking
about assets coming in, we are talking about different
capabilities being brought into Fire and Emergency.
We need to ensure that those
vehicles, if we're deploying them, are actually safe to be deployed.
We need to make sure that they're maintained properly and they're
safe for our people to deploy. And so, there's no
blanket solution to that. It's actually on a case-by-case
basis
on
what the assets are and how we'll deploy them, which is managed through the
regions at the moment around
what that looks like.
Okay, thank you.
Okay. I think that brings us to the end of that section, which
we thought would be a shorter section.
So we're now moving on to procurement and
maintenance. So I'm just wondering if you've got anything
that you wanted to say first.
Well, just an opening saying
we've certainly recognized that in the past there's
been some inconsistency in some of the procurement
documentation in particular, but processes.
We've been on a procurement improvement roadmap that we've
been applying over a number of years now.
So making some good steps forward through
there. But it's certainly an area that when we look
back at some of the procurement decisions in the past could've
been more robust through.
Okay, thank you. And I think, Tim, I'm looking to you
first for comments.
Okay.
You're fine.
You just mentioned the roadmap that was
part of the
procurement improvement program.
Mm-hmm.
Is that correct?
The roadmap was completed in
2025.
Is that right?
But as part of that, you also implemented a new
procurement operating model.
Correct.
And that was in 2022.
So that was right at the start of that four-year improvement plan.
Correct.
Before you even had the roadmap.
And
effectively, am I right in reading from your submission, it didn't work?
Correct.
So you implemented the solution at the start of it before you
had the roadmap and knew what it looked like, and now we've
effectively got rid of that new model and
we've gone back to business units with the central procurement supply team.
Correct.
It feels like another example of reactionary
decision making.
Something's gone wrong, let's try this new procurement thing, and now, oh crap,
that one hasn't worked either. We're going to have to try something else.
Yes, so we did seek advice on what would be the most effective procurement
structure for Fire and Emergency in 2022, expert advice, and
followed that expert advice in the design of that procurement team.
And it's fair to say that we implemented that structure-
Yep
... and it did not work. And so in 2023,
2024, we said, "This does not seem to be serving the organization well.
We need to have the courage to have another look at that procurement structure and
change it," and that's what we did.
Mm-hmm.
The roadmap and the change in structure occurred together as
a way of attempting to really improve our procurement
performance,
and the roadmap was completed alongside the new structure of the team.
So I don't mind the fact that you're willing to acknowledge it's good to hear, but
you're willing to acknowledge, "Hey, this hasn't worked.
We need to go back." I guess it's the decision to go there at the start.
If I read some of the things from your submission, good faith
decisions have often prioritized practical outcomes and operational needs,
sometimes ahead of best practice processes.
Look, I won't go through it all, but I guess the point is we see in a lot of this,
there's a lot focused on process and not enough focus
on production, right? There's lots of
compliance and,
but this is about outcomes, right?
This is about actually getting
appliances on the run. So have we got caught up in the
process and what the operating model is and all of this stuff?
Not from my perspective.
Yeah.
There was a lot of pressure on our procurement performance in 2022, and this
committee was also involved in that process.
We were genuinely trying not to follow an operating model,
but really to try and say, "How do we structure our procurement function so it
serves the organization well?" We went and looked at other
Crown entities and government departments.
What do they do in their procurement function? What can we learn from that?
And that's how we structured the approach going forward.
But it's very fair to say that that did not serve the organization well.
So I wouldn't characterize it as
being overtaken by operating models
Or anything like that, but really trying to get a structure that would serve the
organization well.
And it appeared-
Sorry
... Sorry. Just
looking back in reflection of that, the organization wasn't
ready for the maturity or didn't have the maturity for the model
of procurement that was put in place initially.
So, once that was recognized, that's why it wasn't working.
That's when the decision was made, well, how do we do this different so we can have
a more progressive improvement towards where we need to be
with improvement.
And you said you looked at other government agencies, like I'm thinking about NZDF
that took six of those 36 man chassis.
They took them to Fraser Fire, who built your Tranche 1
body,
and they had them in service by 2024.
We didn't even have a
functioning...
Well, we tested one prototype at that point,
but it wasn't in use, and they had them in use.
They've got
a replacement plan. They know that in 2041 they start the next plan for the next
round. I'm trying to work out how they can execute it
with the exact same chassis that came off the boat that
Defense have got,
and
can we... I don't know. Should we be working with them in terms of
what their procurement team are doing? Because it's obviously worked.
So,
my understanding of that time is that the Defense
procurement was through our process.
So they were part of the same
order that we put through for that.
For the chassis.
And six of those went through to-
Yes
... for the chassis.
But then they got a body built on them and got them introduced into service by
2024, and we didn't even have a functioning one in the country at that point.
Mm.
And ultimately, the delay in ours was caused by the cracking
that came through and finding a recognition-
That was Tranche 1, but Tranche 2, we're talking Tranche 2 here with-
Okay
... the six NZDF were from Tranche 2. You had nobody, they had six.
Mm.
They had those six built up by 2024 and in operational service regularly and
have been ever since. Do your records say that at that point you
had 28 in the UK-
Mm
... still not in service. You had one with ECM that hadn't come back.
You had one with AngloCo that had come back, been tested, but quote, "Sat in the
workshops ever since."
Mm.
My point is really that it's not just about the physical
appliance, it's about the capability that we're introducing.
Yeah.
And do they have something more robust?
Or when you've looked at other government departments, I pick on NZDF because they
took six of your 36.
Mm.
Is there someone that's got that, that can actually just focus, so you don't have
to focus on the process, you just focus on the product
and get it onto the run.
Mm.
It's a fair observation.
But we haven't done any...
I thought you'd say, "Yes, we've done lots of thinking about this, and here's what
we want," or, "Here's why we can't do it through Defense because of X, Y, Z,"
but...
Well, I think if you look again at the procurement of the Type
1s and 2s, that's been a successful procurement
process that's gone through there.
Yeah.
So, the Type 3 is
being complicated by the tail of the legacy
challenges that are set there. So that is the complication that's set
there.
But the whole procurement process
hasn't demonstrated as being broken because we have had those successes.
What it is, is lifting up to actually say, "What are the things that have gone
right, and how do we make sure that we can do that as a systemic
approach to how we deliver procurement for appliances?"
Yeah. Okay. Well, look, I'll say this and then I'll shut up.
But it just seems to me that there's a lot of focus
on processes. There's lots of layers of documentation.
I made this point before. There's a lot of talk about business units and our
business foundations, and that's what covers our fleet as a strategic
priority. But we're not a business.
You're an operational service.
And it seems that we could just go and get, and I like the fact you're
talking about turnkey, but an 80% solution that's available 100% of the time
sounds a lot better to me than 100% solution that is not available because,
in your quotes around your aerial appliances, design
changes taking place all the way through, including in the delivery phase.
The constant changes still
changes happening with AngloCo in terms of the latest Type 3.
Engineering and re-engineering, and it just seems we need to get, as Mr.
Foster said earlier, 10 a year onto the run every year forever.
And if we could move away from being hampered by
process and focused on outputs and production
alone just, and accepting that 80% solution.
Anyway.
Okay. Thank you. Limongia.
Thank you. Probably more Sup now, but following on from
Tim's questioning.
In terms of the planning ahead five years, so you've taken us through the
process in terms of today's agenda,
how confident will you be in terms of moving forward to your
five-year plan that you've got, the procurement
strategy because you've changed the pace in the
last few years and now you've had some success.
Mm.
As you're building the procurement model to be more efficient,
in the next couple of years, will you be on
budget and will you be able to produce what you're after?
But I think what we're building there, we've got
better documentation, better record keeping, better compliance,
and certainly,
applying stronger contract management across those to actually ensure that those
procurements are successful. So,
that gives me the confidence that as an organization,
we're learning, we're applying those learnings to make sure that we
can be successful across the different procurement aspects.
And will 80%, or is there a large percentage of that
that will be on some sort of digital platform that is available
nationwide for your firehouses and your fire stations, given
that there has been, in the past, in some of the hearings, we've heard that
there's quite the manual system But obviously moving to AI and
digital systems so that
you've got a good solution for the right fit.
Are you confident that the planning instruments that you have are on
the right track, and that you are able to deliver?
I think one of the things that's
been missing in the past has been the transparency, and
transparency internally,
so that our people can see what the
procurement pathway and plan is.
Not everyone will always be happy with the plan,
but certainly when people can't see the picture, it becomes very
frustrating around understanding why decisions are made and how
decisions are made. So that greater transparency, I think, will
certainly help the organization and our firefighters
in particular, who get frustrated when things go wrong, have
a greater sense of confidence
in not only what's happening and when it's going to happen, but actually
why it's going to happen as well.
Thank you.
Okay, thank you. Andy.
Yeah, thank you, and if the host can get my video working again, that'd be
very helpful too. Because I can't do it from this end.
Hopefully, that'll work now. Yeah, brilliant.
There you go.
Excellent. Thank you. Look, what I wanted to ask was,
Tim mentioned Fraser
who, just around the corner in the Hutt Valley, you keep on talking about
international
delivery arrangements.
Is there any-- We kind of like things being built in New Zealand as a party
philosophy. Is there any particular reason that you're not using them?
As he said, if NZDF have been using them, got
them on the road and operating very, very quickly, and you still haven't
managed it,
is there some reason that you don't seem to be particularly keen on them?
It's not that we're not particularly keen on, and I certainly
acknowledge and note the changes in the procurement guidelines
around the
weighting around New Zealand procurement that sits in there,
and we'll certainly be applying that as part of our process going forward.
But we have followed the procurement guidelines as part of that process.
So obviously, in your view, that meant that they weren't competitive at that point
in time, so you were getting a better arrangement somewhere
else.
Um-
But you're not actually getting the engines on the road, which is
slightly problematic.
Again, with the Type Threes, if you look at the Type Threes, some of those
delays
have been very frustrating, and also came from
a
varying number of reasons.
But as far as getting appliance on the road, again, say
across the
range of types that we've procured, there has been successes that
have sat through there as well on some of them. But not the Type Threes.
I guess you gave us the defense that you've managed to procure Type
Ones and twos.
Mm-hmm.
But struggled with the rest. That's a little bit like the All Blacks turning up and
saying, "We played one game well, and then we did a lousy job the next time,"
and expect people to be satisfied with it.
Well, I think we've been
dissatisfied with the Type Threes rather than the rest,
and I think that is why the focus is on how do we deal with
the legacy, what does it look like for the next generation?
And I'm also bringing in an independent advisor
that can actually look at our whole end-to-end process.
I
would be surprised if they come in and they don't find other things that we can
improve on them. That is the whole purpose of bringing them in, to give advice to
myself, to give advice to the board on the areas that we can
really pull through and strengthen across the
end-to-end process and how it's aligned.
So, that's going to really help us going forward to have a greater
confidence
that we're going to get the procurement correct going forward.
So, if I go back to
Type Threes,
in the last almost 10 years, you have
delivered one a year. You're expecting to deliver
roughly 13 per year.
Yeah.
Looking at the performance to date, what's going to give us confidence that you're
actually going to be able to do that?
Because it's great to have all the processes, the plans, and the documentation,
everything. But at the moment, the proof's not in the pudding.
Yeah.
And at what point do you actually say, "Well, we're just not
doing this. We're not delivering."
Yeah, and
you're effectively talking about assurance there and-
Well, yeah, I am, because at what point if you said you want to deliver
122-
Yep
... Type Threes in the next
nine years. You've delivered 10 in the last nine.
That's a huge step up.
I would imagine DIA will be all over you, and the minister will
be all over you, making sure that you're actually
starting to deliver at a rate which is 13 times or 12
and a bit times what you've been delivering in the last decade.
Hmm.
Yeah, and like I said, to give us that
confidence, we're bringing in that independent advisor to actually have a look at
that. Audit New Zealand has looked over
the way that we've been procuring, especially around the Type Ones
and Threes, to see that we've got a systemic approach that
we can use year on year on year on that.
And the board chair
of two weeks has already made it very clear
that we need to do better in the area of our fleet, our
Type Three, and our procurement processes to meet.
So the board will be having a very...
I can't speak for the board chair, can speak for himself in that regard, but
he's made clear expectations of what he expects coming into
the organization.
I guess, Kerry, I'm not just looking at whether you've got nice tidy
processes and you're all recency. You say, "This is a beautiful process.
It's got all the integrity wrapped around it and all the other sort of things in
there."
No.
But I still haven't got any engines.
You know, that's ultimately, as Mr Costley said
earlier,
we actually want to see new engines replacing old ones, which are
now getting out of date.
I certainly appreciate the frustration, and I have the
frustration myself at
being able to get engines on the road for our frontline people,
and making sure that they can have what they need that's not going to break down.
And it is about making sure that
they're robust and safe and
I can certainly give you our assurance that we're doing best endeavors to actually
meet the timelines that we put in place.
But also can't anticipate
what other challenges or issues we'll come across that need to be rectified.
And what we need to do when we come across those is actually stop,
take stock, and to understand what the problem is and ensure that they're
safe and effective for our people.
And we'll continue to do that and ensure that we're driving
the expediency.
I go back, though, to two other things I'll ask.
One is the
turnkey versus bespoke approach.
And the more that you can make it simple, you're more likely to get it right.
Yeah.
And so some confidence around that will be useful.
And just the other one is, are there any
lessons that you can pick up from other people?
We've already heard NZDF. I'm also aware that
all the airports, well, I think all of them around the country, or
nearly all of them, certainly maybe the smallest ones don't have them, they've all
got fire engines as well.
Now, they may be easier, I don't know, they may be easier to
procure because they're there to do one job.
But they seem to be quite good at replacing them on
time and on budget, as far as I'm aware, the ones I've seen.
We'll certainly be reaching out to
all the different
like bodies, including across Australia,
to fully understand how they're operating and
whether there's things in there that can actually improve our ability to
deliver and get the trucks on the run in a really meaningful time.
Sorry, did you say we will be or we have been?
Well, we have been engaging
with different entities across there.
And Jim, can you speak to those or...
Yeah, I think
as we're talking about turnkey solutions and then what other jurisdictions
are doing, I think it's an important component here that we're not buying
a car production line. So even when we say turnkey,
every jurisdiction will be different.
If you go to the UK, where they have local authorities heavily involved in
each kind of fire authority, they have subtle differences for their
trucks. Across the different jurisdictions in Australia, they have
subtle differences for their trucks.
So there's always degrees of variance and change
there.
We are part of a kind of grouping of the Australian states, so
we have regular dialogues with different jurisdictions around new
capabilities, new approaches. When it comes to actually then going
to the market, of course, we have to conform to New Zealand procurement rules.
And then frankly, we are competing in a very congested
market where there are a small number of providers, and several of
those providers are taken up with high funding organizations.
So again, when we turn up and we say we need to buy, call it 10 a
year, two a year, depending on what the truck type is, actually for some of those
producers, we're just not actually a customer of choice.
And so we're then kind of offsetting what their capacity is
to support us. So yeah, we do engage with Australia.
We do keep a very close look at what else is happening overseas,
and then we feed that into our design planning and our considerations.
You've just said you're basically using scale of the organization
as an excuse for why it's difficult.
That doesn't seem to have caused any problems for NZDF, which were much
smaller than you in terms of the number of vehicles they
require. And airports, they're buying,
even a reasonable sized airport, it has
maybe three.
They don't seem to have any difficulty.
So in terms of NZDF, and without getting into their
procurement process, but they
purchased the six MAN cab chassis on the back of the
defense-established
contract. They chose to have their body build done by
Fraser Fire for their six.
We went through a different process in terms of four of their kind of the wave
two of the trucks, the ones we're working through with
AngloCo at the moment. So there are some differences there.
We note in terms of conversation around Fraser Fire Rescue,
we're working with them on other trucks.
At the moment, they have three of the type fives in their workshops right now
that they are building for us. So ultimately, we engage the market, we do
so in accordance with the government procurement rules, and we work through that
tender process.
I wouldn't say that we're trying to
use scale as an excuse. Been very
open and I think open through the submission as well around the
challenges that we've seen across our process.
And the core lesson that I see in here is
that
the procurement of the really complex safety critical
appliances means that it needs to be joined up and
governed across all the different components, whether that's from
the operational requirements to the procurement pathway, to the
contractor
management, the supplier
performance in there, how we
test the appliance, how we train the appliance.
It needs to be an end-to-end process, and I've
Looking back, there's certainly areas there that we can do better.
And I know that talks to process,
but
making sure that that's fully
scoped out at the start of the process means that you're successful at the end and
you get the delivery at the end.
That's been a learning for the organization.
It's been something that I've seen through the type threes that we haven't done
well. So I'm not trying to make excuses for that.
It
has evolved how it's evolved. And now as an organization, our
focus has to be very much on how do we make sure we get that right going forward.
Not try to blame others for where we are or
the scope or the scale or the decisions that have been made
of the past. It's about learning and how we take that forward from there,
to give you as
the committee, whose role is to
actually test and challenge the assurance that we can get it right.
And we can't do that for you today, because ultimately,
until we deliver,
you're not going to be satisfied in that things, and rightly so, because there's
been some questions asked, and the organization, I think, is being very
upfront about some of those challenges that we've
faced and we've seen. But we certainly have a commitment to
getting that right and making sure that we can change that going forward.
And look, Chair, if I could just finish with one last thing.
Very quick. Thank you.
Yep, you mentioned subtle differences between New Zealand's requirements,
apparent requirements, and, say, the Australians, et cetera.
And I go back to what Tim Costley was asking, which is,
do you actually say, "Well, look, we're not going to make things too complicated
for ourselves. We're going to ignore or leave out those subtle differences,
and just make life less complicated for ourselves, so we actually get
engines on the road."
Yeah. Megan's just come from Australia, so I might get you just to speak to that,
Megan.
Yeah. I think that's a really good observation.
I've worked across three jurisdictions in Australia.
And
as an operational firefighter,
we
rightly so want everything that we can get on our trucks.
And I think part of my role is leading the
workforce in understanding that
sometimes there needs to be compromise. As Mr.
Costley said, 80% having trucks on the road
to our needs I think is really important.
We're
having conversations in operations around, for example, the type
fours at the moment.
We did a desktop with Australia. There's 10 different types of type
fours in use in Australia. Only two of those
could meet our axle weights. So the conversations you were talking
about is unless we get those compromises
in, we either have to
get an exemption or we have to compromise on other aspects.
So I think we will mature as an operational part of the
organization when we realize we've got to be really
specific with our requirements and understand sometimes we can't
have everything if we've got a restriction in cubic
space or cubic weight.
Okay, Melissa, is this a start?
Yes, it is.
Yeah. Okay, I'll go to you. Thanks, Indy.
Thanks very much. If I could actually go to, I know we've been talking about
procurement of fire trucks, but could I actually go to the ICT
procurement and the budget that you have?
That's in relation to question number 15 of the
post-hearing questions and the answers you've actually provided.
The question that I'd like to ask is that you actually talk about the business
intelligence project
which includes fleet fault logging, and that's
$2.941 million.
Could you actually explain what portion of that is actually
fleet logging, as in fault logging, because as far as I
know, and I've spoken to firefighters who actually
say that they log everything on paper.
So what have you actually provided with that budget?
Thank you.
I'll ask Darryl to speak to the budget elements of that, which he's just finding
the right place for.
So we
are implementing at the moment a fleet logging system.
It's in pilot at this stage. It is built on the ServiceNow platform.
And that will provide a digital electronic method
for firefighters and others to log
faults with appliances and have those faults addressed.
So that's in the early stages. So we've been in the build phase on the
ServiceNow platform to put that fault management system in place.
When is that going to actually be put in place?
So it's piloting now with one location, which is the Wellington
location, and then it will be rolled out progressively
over the next six months
region by region.
Okay.
Yeah.
The operational component actually includes land mobile radios, masts
and poles and station turnout costs are actually supporting
640 stations and approximately 2,000 vehicles.
If that is the case, the budget actually says mobility,
availability messaging service, appliance cell phones,
end-user devices, all of those. End-user device
is 300,000,
appliance cell phone is 518,000, availability messaging service is
623,000, mobility is 662,000. What are those for?
I can answer that. Our mobility in our fire
appliances, if you look at the type threes are
an
And access to data
for mapping, for building our plans,
it gives our people information in the field, and
it's a critical part of ensuring their safety and the best
tactics can be used at what they're facing.
That's one example of what mobility means.
And then-
So the land mobile radio system doesn't actually provide that,
which actually costs more than $7 million.
We still need to have
understanding of where our people are in the field, have good
communications when we're out there, so having
the best radio comms, et cetera, is a really critical
part of being a firefighter.
So the end user device, 301,000,
301,000 is, I guess, and that's
one. Appliance cell phones, that's another, and that's
518,000. So which of them is actually the device that you're
talking about?
We have multiple layers of communication on an appliance.
This gives us redundancy.
Obviously.
Yeah. So we have tablets that give people, just
like a, not an iPad, but similar to an iPad.
We've got
mobile phones, gives us another layer of connectivity, and we
have our radios both in the appliance and then portable
radios as well. So we've got multi layers of communication in the
field.
Right. So what is risk reduction
involved? $186,000.
Uh.
So that is the build of the evacuation system that we're
renewing presently, and it'll be a partial spend on that evacuation
system,
which essentially receives all of the reports throughout the year
of evac- trial evacuations, and then summarizes
those reports and understands where their issues and risks are.
So it'll be part of that suite of products.
So that is not included in the business intelligence portion, which is nearly $3
million.
The business intelligence is directed towards the fault system.
Right.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks, Melissa.
Mike.
Thank you. Actually, mine's a follow-up to, Melissa's question as
well.
Because there's been no national defect fleet recording system, and obviously it's
now been implemented.
When was that decision made to do that?
To which to-
To implement a national defect fleet recording system.
I might have to come back to you with the absolute date on
when that decision was made. But effectively,
we maintain and effectively
manage the maintenance across the country.
So what we have is it's really fragmented across the multitude of
suppliers that we have, our maintenance contracts.
Some of it is held by our people. And so,
that new approach has actually given us greater visibility at
a national level around what it means for us.
Do you have a rough idea when that decision was made?
I wouldn't want to mislead you, so I will come back on that.
Because one of the things I note, and I'm just, once fully rolled out to all
stations, it will strengthen governance.
Yeah.
And I'm just also wondering what the conversation has been between, like,
management and the board around, obviously,
the visibility of defects across the fleet-
Mm-hmm
... and whether they were asking any questions to management
around not having a system in place.
Well, like I said, it's not about not having a system in place.
It's been fragmented to have a look at the
national level around what those things mean.
So at a local level,
those contracts are being managed, and we've got staff across the country who are
dedicated to managing the individual contracts.
But as a collective to actually see where are
things starting to evolve that
might be systemic across the fleet that need to be addressed, that's what
we'll get out of this new system that will allow us to do it.
Yeah, I understand that. And I guess my question's more around
was there any concern raised by the board about the fact that
you, you're talking about it being fragmented.
Was there any concerns raised by the board about this?
Or is this
purely from management?
Well, there's certainly,
yeah, it's about the level of reporting necessary that we've given to the board
around that, to look at that from a,
I guess, a systemic view as opposed to the ongoing
management of the different maintenance and pieces that are going through.
So as management, you were giving the board, I guess, a view
of
the
maintenance issues, that it was all a bit fragmented.
Mm-hmm.
Were the board saying, "This isn't good enough"?
Or were the board just accepting what you were giving?
I'm just trying to work out, like-
Yeah
... where this is coming from, the driver.
Whether it's management or the board.
I'm trying to work out, like, what the board knew and what the board was asking
for.
Yeah. I mean, I don't have visibility of what discussions the board
had outside of us, but certainly,
from a,
discussions around the
systemic approach of maintenance
certainly was something that we've driven from inside the organization, as I
would expect from a management perspective, to make sure we're addressing this.
And just one last question.
Because you referred to, obviously, when
appliances are unavailable to proceed or not available,
and then you have your network deployment.
Yeah.
So I guess for another appliance will probably come from the closest station to the
TID.
Yeah.
That didn't have to affect your response time. Is that correct?
Like, you have an eight-minute response time.
Yeah.
If you have an appliance that's unavailable-
Mm-hmm
... and you therefore have to deploy from another station-
Different one. Mm
... your response time's gonna be impacted
Well, it really depends on where in this response stream
that appliance is. Because we don't just normally
send one appliance to a call, we send a multitude.
If it's the nearest appliance that
breaks down or isn't available, then it will have
a delay in that.
But you also can't necessarily quantify that
around availability
only. The challenges and response
around traffic congestion, around...
There's a multitude of factors that layer into the
time it takes to respond from wherever to an event.
But it would only have the effect on that if it was the closest
station that was going to respond to that to be available.
And I guess we saw
from the data that there's been an uptick of appliances that are
out of action.
Mm-hmm.
And so would that not therefore concern you quite immensely, the fact that
obviously we're starting to see a bit of a surge, which corresponds to the
age-
Mm-hmm
... and therefore the impact that may have on response
times?
Yeah, I don't want to diminish the
impact that has on our firefighters and on
the frustration that has when it's not available.
But certainly, at a national level, we look at it from a national response of what
are our timelines from the network to be able to respond to
individual events. So what's our performance on a national
level to be able to
respond when Kiwis call us?
Okay, thank you.
And we do report on that in our SBEs.
Yeah.
On our response times.
Sorry, I'm-
We report to government on our response times.
Through our accountability documents-
Yeah
... and our SBE.
Yeah.
Did it improve last financial year, the response time?
Again, they're areas that we
try to get within, but there's a
number of factors that mean that we can sometimes be outside
of those-
I guess, actually, a really simple question.
Okay. Yeah.
Did the response time improve last financial year?
Can't remember off the top of my head.
No, we'd have to come back to that.
We'd have to come back to that.
So we're morphing into our last section now, so I'm going to
ask
Tim to speak, and then right at the end, I'll give you the
chance to. So Tim.
Yeah, I just want to ask some really specific subs, just to pick up two things.
Melissa asked about two-way radios and trucks.
Has Finn's been removing any two-way radios from
trucks and volunteer stations recently?
Sorry, I-
Removing radios.
Have you been taking two-way radios off
trucks and volunteer stations,
specifically in Canterbury?
I've been told that-
No
... stations there have been losing
radios from their trucks.
On-
Certainly nothing that I'm aware of from a national approach to removing
radios from volunteer appliances, but we would have
to check that locally and come back to you.
Okay. And in terms of the
fault logging, as I understand it at the moment, until you can bring in a digital
system, it's literally a paper logbook in the truck.
Mm-hmm.
That's how faults get reported.
Yeah. So, if you have a look at page 18 of the submission, I
think 2.34 to 2.46
takes you through that process.
So when it's done, they literally write down, "This door is not quite right," or
this, whatever it might be.
Mm-hmm.
It then gets ticked off once it's gone to the workshop.
It doesn't say if any work was done.
It doesn't say if the fault was confirmed and it was fixed versus if
they couldn't confirm the fault or it actually is acceptable, so it can stay in the
limit.
Mm-hmm.
It can stay as it is.
It seems pretty
rudimentary really, right?
Mm-hmm.
There's not even a record of if things were fixed.
Is
that an issue currently? Do you have any actual situational awareness of
the state of the fleet if all you've got
is people write down something on paper and it got a tick, which might mean it was
fixed, or it might mean it was actually fine?
Yeah. So
again, if I take you back to the submission, it clearly shows the
times that we use those logbooks for minor
defects in there. If there's more material defects than that,
they're addressed straight away through the maintenance providers.
But that is one of the reasons
why we're implementing ServiceNow as a maintenance
solution that will allow better visibility so
that our firefighters can see when they log issues, what's the status
and how it comes back, and they've been repaired or not.
Because the next generation trucks have got a mean time between defect and mean
time to fix
defect and service agent request metrics, right?
So you're going to need to be able to capture all of that data because I assume
that the provider, do they have a through-life sustainment
contract, Emergency One, with the next generation?
Of the maintenance?
Yes.
So our ongoing maintenance is contracted across the country to
maintenance providers within
the country.
So if you're assessing the success of those next
generation trucks, measuring things like mean time between
defect, number of service agent
requests,
what do you do with that data if
you're not...
In this case, Emergency One, can you hold them to account if they don't reach a
certain performance level or not?
That is the whole purpose of
Having a more robust IT system in to support that through the
service now, so that we have better visibility of that.
At the moment, like I say, it's very fragmented-
Yeah
... in our understanding of that.
Even if it was a challenge, we would have an inability to actually keep the
supplier accountable for that.
So let's say that you bring this new system in and it fixes everything.
You now have all the
time in these categories. Can you then take that information and say to a
provider, "Hey, your trucks were meant to meet these metrics.
They haven't."
Yeah.
Is there a commercial comeback? Is there a
clawback into them that gets us...
Unless Jim knows the answer to that, we'll have to come back to you with that
because that's a contractual-
I don't know for this specific contract.
And what I would note is, within our approach to contract
management more broadly, we are bringing in far more controls,
which will dovetail into data such as this, which will allow us to go
back to suppliers, but we would need to come back to you with the
specifics on this one.
Yeah. It certainly says that your future project reviews will include timeliness,
quality, and cost, use of fault reporting, and in-service performance metrics.
Mm-hmm.
But if there's not a commercial-
Introducing that.
Yeah. If you've got no hook to get into them for that, then that's
interesting, and it's good for you to know where you're at in terms of when you
have to replace vehicles. As I understand it, the AngloCo only
has payment milestones and delivery dates.
Is that all that
we were
measuring for that contract?
For instance, was the board tracking...
Well, the board would've been tracking nothing, but were we tracking
anything other than payment milestones and
delivery dates for them? Are there other metrics built into that contract
in the AngloCo type premium?
Yeah.
We'd need to come back on that, like I don't have-
There's certainly
milestone acceptances through the term of that contract.
But again, around the specifics of that contract, we'd have to come back to you.
But it's been clearly
identified, there's areas of our contract management that need to
be matured and
grown through there. And so,
ensuring that we're, like I said before, having that
end-to-end process of what's our operational requirements, what's our contract
management, what's the design of the contracts, the design of the
appliances. All that needs to be end-to-end process
that's governed in one way. Not looked at as
bespoke elements that sit there across how
those contracts come to fruition.
So, my final one on that, AngloCo, man, those
trucks,
they came from Europe.
Mm-hmm.
They got freighted to New Zealand.
Then, because just after that was done is when the cracking emerged, so I
understand that.
Mm-hmm.
They got parked up.
Then we freighted them back to the UK.
So they've now done their first trip around the world, and then they got the
body built, and then they've come back here.
And they appear to have been parked up for some time, particularly those last 12
before they get resolved. What is the cost of having to park
up those trucks, or the storage cost?
We don't have those figures with me today, but
we can see if we can pull those together.
There was one in your submission that was in the ballpark
of 30,000.
Am I in the right
order of magnitude?
I don't want to mislead you with
information I haven't got on hand.
Okay.
I'd rather take the time to get it right and come back.
And then I understand there was also about 130,000 or
150,000 on top of that for servicing them while they were parked
up.
Like I say, we can come back to you.
Okay. Well, maybe we'll come back with those. Thanks.
I'm just checking. Melissa, is this a sup?
Okay, you go for it, because I've got a primary from Mike.
So you go for it.
You're muted, Mel.
You're muted, yeah, the-
Yeah, sorry. I'm
just on mute. Yes, thank you. This is sup.
You've actually
said that you will come back to us with lots of
the questions that you can actually answer.
This is several times in a row that we've actually sort of
had you at select committee, and this is the inquiry where you should have all of
the answers. So going with that,
the answer to engaging external consultants, you've actually put two,
one, a PR company, and the other one, a law firm, to actually help you with the
inquiry. If you're coming back with more answers, you've already spent more
than $90,000 to pay for these two companies.
How much more do you expect to pay?
Last time we were here, we spoke about the
contracted expertise that we had in to help us.
And
to be
clear, we're not
designed as an organization
to have that sort of expertise that's needed to support
a review of this type as a permanent component of
the organization. So,
we do need to bring that
resource in to support the organization to actually provide the
information that you require to there.
And on top of that,
like we've explained before, a lot of our systems
and the way things have been documented,
need to actually be really interrogated to find the information.
The
legacy of what foreign emergency
is working with from that
document management and ICT components,
is part of the challenge that we have in how we build an
organization that's-
... robust and has that information on our fingertips
to ensure we can make better decisions through there.
So I can't give you a figure on what that will cost, or even
whether
we have that information at our fingertips.
But what I will say is,
we want to be open, we want to be transparent with the select committee, and we're
on a journey of improvement to ensure that what we've
experienced with the type threes in particular,
isn't a journey that we travel again for the organization.
There's been, like I said, a long tail, there's been decisions made along the way,
and our role is to actually work through that, and ensure
that we can get
safe, robust appliances on the run for all of our firefighters to serve New
Zealanders going forward.
How long have you been the CEO? Because the questions that the select committee has
actually provided to you are operational in nature.
There might have been some that weren't, but specifically about
equipments that haven't been delivered, equipments that have
had faults. It's all operational questions.
And the fact that you had to hire outside help, PR company, and law
firm to actually find answers for yourself, and paying exorbitant
amounts of money, actually tells me that you really need to think about how your
organization is actually operating as a CEO.
Yeah. And it is always a balance of whether you
employ those specialist skills permanently, or whether you bring
them in when you need them for the organization.
And that's a balance that we'll continue to assess as we move
forward.
I wasn't talking about the skillsets of the lawyer and the PR company.
I was talking about information that you have at hand about trucks that are
actually at fault, trucks that you've actually implemented and actually are on the
road, and trucks that are not actually on the road.
These are information that you should have at hand as the CEO.
That's what I'm talking about.
Yeah, no, I don't disagree with you at all.
That is information that you should have on hand, and that's why we are looking at
our systems that we have in place,
how we collect information. Even what we're doing now around the service
now to actually have a, not a
fragmented view, but an accurate view
around maintenance across the country,
suggests some of the
systems that we're working for that aren't necessarily
fit for purpose for the organization moving forward.
Yeah, we have had to have an- Okay ... inquiry to get.
Thanks, Melissa. Okay, Mike.
Thank you. I just have a quick sub on that, Melissa's question.
I'm just curious,
what skills didn't you have that you need to have a PR firm to help you with this
process?
Well, I think making sure that
we had a good understanding of what the committee was after,
and being able to understand what the committee was
looking for as far as the breadth of the review into
fleet. It was quite a broad scope that sits in there.
So, what are the real things that
you really want to understand opposed to what we
might be looking at.
And it required a PR firm.
Mm.
My question is, we've received a lot of submissions
around basically saying that the issue's not the fleet, it's a
wider issue, and the fleet's actually a symptom of a bigger problem
within FENZ. How do you respond to that?
I think lots of people look at FENZ as an organization and they
see a fire service that's been around for hundreds of years.
For FENZ as an organization,
it's been around for nine years,
and it's inherited a lot of
legacy challenges of bringing all those together, and
so there is a complex mix in building an organization that's
resilient for New Zealand going forward.
Like I've said, we've got challenges around how we build the right
IT systems and modernize IT systems.
We're obviously aware around the challenges that we have around
the fleet,
our property. So all of our asset classes sit across there.
And at the same time, we need to make sure that we're continuously
applying a seamless delivery of our services into
communities, which I'm really proud of, is the service that we
deliver to communities every day.
So there is a real complexity
in how the organization's coming together, working
to build that and grow that within a constrained fiscal
envelope,
as all organizations need to do. So, we can't do everything at once.
We need to build out the planning. And a lot of the things that you
would expect of an organization to be in place just weren't in place
at the start, and some of that long-term strategic thinking and strategic
planning. So we're moving the organization to doing a lot more
strategic planning and thinking longer term,
rather than the response nature of dealing to things as they come up.
Okay.
And that's a cultural move for the organization as well.
Okay, so
just so I'm clear,
so you're kind of saying, although we're here today and we are
doing an inquiry on the fleet
within FENZ, there's actually other issues that need to be sorted
as well.
I'd say we're balancing our priorities across the number of
challenges that we have as an organization within the funding model that we have.
Yeah, but there's multiple issues, right, within FENZ?
There's some challenges. We've got plans around those, of how we
address them. The asset management plans across our assets really
give a clear picture of how we address those things.
And just like any organization has challenges,
there are things that we need to work through.
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you. Andy.
Yeah, thank you. It was actually a sup to-
That's all good
Sorry?
Yeah. Go for it. That's all good.
Yeah, no. Sup, sup to the original question around,
you've bought all these... Well, I just want to check,
because we had the questions about the carrying cost of, and the parking cost, if
you like, of the engines that you've bought which aren't operational.
But I'm interested in whether you've paid for them,
and the cost of actually holding vehicles for an extended period of time that you
don't own. It's not a parking cost, it's a financing cost.
And whether you actually own them, whether there's any warranty arrangements you've
got with the providers if things are not satisfactory.
Who's carrying the can?
So, Mr Foster, I believe those were fire and
emergencies costs. I'm still trying to isolate those costs.
I've been working on those for a while.
That would be very-
Not difficult. Yeah, sorry, not difficult to isolate in all of the costs.
Yeah, okay. Look, I think it'll be good to understand, because clearly they
can't be insubstantial if you've had these vehicles for quite some time.
You've, as we heard, sent them back to the UK and
back. So that's not going to be cheap.
And if you're paying for that rather than somebody out at the supplier, I think we
want to know that.
Understood.
And what the order of magnitude is.
Okay, thank you. Lamanga. Thanks, Andy. Lamanga.
Thanks, Chair. Just patiently listening.
Kerry, you've talked about asset classes in a number of things
as you've explained to the Select Committee.
Your workforce is your biggest asset class.
Can you highlight the fact that
you've got all these things,
appliances, trucks you talked about in the Select Committee.
What about your workforce and the training and development programs?
Will there be a pivot to ensure that
when you've got new types of trucks and you've got different
pressures, that the workforce in terms of them pivoting
to the requirements of responding to
emergencies?
Yeah, thank you. And,
I guess the focus has been very much on the fleet of
the different asset classes,
because that's the focus of this review.
Very much in our strategy, one of the key threads of that is how we support
our people,
and part of that is training. One of the areas that I've identified that we need to
create some savings so that we can reinvest into the
business is around savings-- Sorry, is around training,
and how we have a
systemic approach to that to ensure that that's fit for,
like I said before, what's a complex environment around
11,800, roughly,
volunteers across the country,
and a dispersed workforce across the country as well to keep them
safe. So very much when I look at people, a lot of the
focus is on how do we create safe systems of work and what are the
things that we're doing to ensure that our people are safe.
And I'm
really proud of the delivery of our service into
communities and in such
varied natures. If you think of the nature of things that our people get deployed
to right across the country every day.
When you look at the safety of our
people and the ability to adapt
and move tactics to ensure they are safe and the public is safe,
I think is extraordinary by our people.
And that's a real credit to the service that is carried out every day,
whether that's being across our career staff, whether that's across our
paid staff. And people agree is their
most important asset,
and that's why the focus of the strategy is around supporting our people in that
area.
Thank you.
Thank you, and the final question goes to Tim.
Oh, thank you.
So just to confirm,
I'll use the Anglica man as an example.
How many of those,
that project that started back in August 2019, how many of those are in use
today, of those 30?
Trench two. We were-
Trench two.
We had three in service, and then
we took those out while we identify
the behavior of the high-pressure delivery
automation.
That's because of the built-in protections, which mean if both, is it
switched off at the same time or turned off, then it will shut down the pump.
High pressures, yeah.
And potentially you get a firefighter on the other end of it that then can't get
water and that.
Yeah. So we spent the day with our specialists last Friday,
understanding how the design is. It's a brand
new,
I guess it's like an autopilot for firefighter pumping.
And it was really for our specialist trainers to understand the behavior of the
pump, under what conditions it behaves.
So I believe-
Is that perhaps a function of us not testing them before we ordered them?
We might have found that out, right?
Well, it was our people had tested them extensively, our operational
testing. It has to be very specific.
But the operational testing was three months after we put the order in for 28.
Yeah. There's a series of things that have to happen at exactly the same
time to get this behavior, and that only was
identified late in the day, so to speak.
So as soon as it was identified, until we understood it,
precautionary and keeping firefighters safety,
Kerry and I had a discussion and we took it offline.
I'd much rather sit here and tell you that three were online today.
No, no, I get it. I'm not questioning the operational decision.
That's not for me to make. But,
I just want to understand where we are.
Can I just ask the board chair, because you've been sitting there politely.
I guess as we sit here and we listen to it, right, seven years ago,
we started a project Seven years later, zero of
the 30 trucks in use for the reasons that we've just heard.
None of them have a warranty on them because that has expired due to
time.
They weren't tested,
possibly at all, but certainly maybe a little bit of acceptance testing at the most
before we placed the order for another 28.
Those 28 have done more travel around the world than I have in the last four
years.
And then there's commercial, 12 of them aren't in use for commercial issues that we
haven't been able to go into here, but there are perhaps other issues lingering in
behind them.
Not to mention the use of contractors and lawyers and things to support this.
What level of comfort do you have right now as a new board chair?
Thank you. Thank you for those, um, insight questions.
Well, my
response would be that the situation is not acceptable.
The fact that we're still dealing with these issues several years
after the procurement began is disappointing for
firefighters, for communities,
for FENZ,
and very concerning for me.
So from my point of view, having just come in,
I've got to make sure that, as chair of the board, and with
the assistance of the other board members,
we put the appropriate assurance and
accountability on management to make
sure that, yes, we've got these historical issues,
but we need to move forward. And throughout this afternoon,
we've covered both areas. The challenges with Type
3 and the fact that even the aerials are not delivered.
But also going back to the points made by
Mr Foster and yourselves, that we need to have
a pipeline of renewals of these appliances and of our
properties, as a mechanical,
systemic...
It should be in our DNA, put it that way. Just like firefighting is.
So from an organizational point of view, that would be my challenge,
that coming into this organization and taking into account all
the issues that the organization may have inherited
but is also facing right now, we need to find a
way forward to give confidence and credibility to
everyone that we serve.
Thank you. I think people
would understand that answer, and I think certainly people want to see
accountability. Can I finish by asking you
where that accountability sits with the board?
And I want to make the point that I think when any Kiwi dials 111 and asks
for the fire service, they should and will have huge confidence and trust
in those that are coming out to serve them.
Most of them volunteers, in smaller communities around New Zealand,
a really professional, paid workforce as well.
And I see the value that they add on the ground.
My question is, what value have the board added over this period because of all the
issues that we've talked about, and I take that the most
visible one that this committee has talked about in at least five bespoke meetings
now with FENZ is the MAN
Tranche 2. And I understand that you weren't the chair at the time,
but the committee has been misinformed, possibly misled, including by the
previous board chair,
even around what role the board took, what questions were
asked. There is no record of them. Apparently, there were subcommittees that might
have discussed them, but there is absolutely no record of more
than two years of the board ever asking about one of the most high
profile issues that we have been dealing with here.
Not to mention the other things that we've just covered now, like what more would
it take for every other board member to resign?
Or where would the point come that you would not have confidence
in the board that you are leading?
Those are profound
questions.
Look, just to start off with, you made a very good point.
The public see the firefighters and the fire engines.
The firefighters,
they see whether the organization behind them
actually works, the engine works.
And as chair, it's my job to make sure they both work.
So what we've been
covering this afternoon is there seems to be, there is, I know from
my own experience, very high regard for firefighters,
for those individuals who go out and help others.
And it seems that the organization
has let that down.
So what would it take for board members to look at
themselves and see whether they've been adding value or not?
Well, I would say if any of them have been watching today, that would
be a fair start. But
I would be expecting the board members to actually do
their job,
just like I would be doing. We have to make sure that
we focus on good governance,
provide support to management, but hold them to account.
And where they're struggling because we have systemic issues, we need to
address them.
At this point in time, I think I can say no more,
but give you the assurance that I hope that I can make a difference.
That's wonderful. Thank you, Ravin.
Kerry, is there anything you wanted to finish with?
Just now, I just really want to thank the committee.
It's your role to
really put a focus on the organization and
coming out of that, it helps us to improve and help us to move forward.
And hopefully you've seen we've been really transparent in
exposing the challenges that we've come up with and engaging with it.
So, I look forward to continuing to work with the committee,
whether in this capacity or
just as the normal hearings that we have.
But thank you for your focus and look forward to see what comes through your
review.
Thank you. And thank you very much for your time this afternoon.
And thank you, Ravin, as well for coming in.
Thank you.
Right. Thank you, everyone. We're going to move into closed session shortly